<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The laver of the heart; or Bath of sanctification Preached at Pauls Crosse the first of September last, 1615. By Gabriel Price, minister and preacher of Gods word.</title>
            <author>Price, Gabriel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 172 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10061</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20306</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102929</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838689</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838689</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3077</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10061)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3077)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1150:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The laver of the heart; or Bath of sanctification Preached at Pauls Crosse the first of September last, 1615. By Gabriel Price, minister and preacher of Gods word.</title>
                  <author>Price, Gabriel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 160 [i.e. 158] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston, for Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A sermon.</note>
                  <note>Pages 54-55 missing in number only.</note>
                  <note>Print show-through; some pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3077:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3077:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LAVER OF THE HEART; <hi>OR</hi> BATH OF SANCTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FICATION. Preached at <hi>Pauls Croſſe</hi> the firſt of September laſt,
1615.</p>
            <p>By GABRIEL PRICE Miniſter and Preacher of Gods
<hi>Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISAY. 1.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Waſh you, make you cleane, take away the euill of your workes from before mine eyes: ceaſe to doe euill, learne to doe well, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONDON, Imprinted by <hi>Felix Kyngston,</hi> for <hi>Thomas Man.</hi> 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3077:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3077:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE HIS VE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie good Lord and Patron, ROBERT Lord RICH, Baron of <hi>Leez:</hi> GABRIEL PRICE wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>all grace, peace, and ioy in</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing, with increaſe of Honor <hi>in this life, and eternall</hi> hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe in the life to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue preſumed (which I haue lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g purpoſed) to offer vnto your Honor: ſome poore token of that dutie, which bindeth mee vnto your
<pb facs="tcp:3077:3"/>Lordſhip, while life la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth: hauing gotten ſome fit occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to expreſſe my loue, I thought not to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termit the ſame; but ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to ſhew my minde and poore abilitie, wherein I may doe your Honor any ſeruice. Therefore after I had yeelded to publiſh this Sermon, I remembred the bleſſed &amp; holie Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> penning and publiſhing the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly ſtorie and bleſſed Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt, did dedicate the ſame to one <hi>Theophilus,</hi> a noble man of
<pb facs="tcp:3077:3"/>ſingular credit and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie; which moued me to make choice of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour, to become a Patron &amp; refuge vnto my poore and ſimple meditations, in a Sermon preached at <hi>Paules Croſſe</hi> (as the title ſheweth): and is a Treatiſe tending to ſanctification: which, according to the time, I haue, amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, brought my preſent; and (as I hope) contrarie to <hi>Mithridates</hi> ſword, is more pretious and richer within, then it is without: and which, with the New
<pb facs="tcp:3077:4"/>yeere, as a New-yeeres gift, I humbly preſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Lordſhip, that vnder the ſhadow of your Honorable acceptance, it may finde ſome reſt and reliefe. To whom being diligently read, and often meditated vpon, I doubt not, but it will be fruitfull to inflame a zeale of Gods glorie, and furtherance of his religion.</p>
            <p>Wherefore my humble deſire is, your Honour would vouchſafe the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage hereof, &amp; then (I doubt not but) more lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:3077:4"/>then my ſelfe will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept my good will; and good men will helpe mee with their prayers to God, for the encreaſe of his grace, to the further inlo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the kingdome of his holy ſonne Ieſus.</p>
            <p>Now the very God of peace ſanctifie your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour throughout, and in the peruſing hereof, to meaſure the commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to the glorie of God, by the liking and feeling of your own heart: ſo ſhal I haue what I deſire, and my paines ſhall bee more
<pb facs="tcp:3077:5"/>then ſufficientlie recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced. Praying vnto God that you may liue long, to the benefit of your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, the aduancement of your Honour, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of learning; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all, that your whole ſpirit, and ſoule and bodie may bee kept blameleſſe, vnto the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, to his glorie, who ſhall glorifie you in the Heauens.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3077:5"/>
            <head>TO THE GODLY and well diſpoſed Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing taken in hand to entreat of this place of Scripture (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my poore ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, wherewith God hath enabled me) at the ſundry motions &amp; earneſt requeſts of ſome of my friends (ſuch as feare God) I was earneſtly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to put the ſame in print, for the benefit (as they ſaid) of others, whoſe chriſtian deſier, I take in this caſe, as a ſufficient calling hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; neither do I yet ſee, how I could haue made them a denyall, without ſome preiudice to their ſoules, and ſome checke vnto mine owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. For the matter it ſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining
<pb facs="tcp:3077:6"/>
               <hi>(The Lauar of the heart, or the Bath of Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion)</hi> I confeſſe is of that excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, that it requireth both large and deepe diſcourſes, wherein both lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and godly haue not bin wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. In this corruption of nature it is not poſsible to do any thing ſo exactly well, but will bee carped at, depraued and ſlandered; ſo that who offereth any thing to the ſight of the world, muſt make ready his backe for the deepe ſurrowes of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry byting cenſurer.<note place="margin">Pſa
1.9 3.</note> Therefore who am I? that I ſhould take vpon me to ſet forth and publiſh any thing; the vnworthieſt I confeſſe of many hundreds, and the vnableſt of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands: yet ſeeing many things more ſimple, leſſe needfull, and profitable, are not only ſuffered, but alowed to come abroad: I am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t altogether diſcouraged, neither
<pb facs="tcp:3077:6"/>hath any man iuſt cauſe to accuſe me in this my honeſt enterpriſe. And ſo much the leſſe becauſe my care hath been to bee ſound and plaine, for the benefit of the ſimplier ſort, and eſpecially for the ſatisfying of ſuch honeſt and good hearts, as deſired to peruſe that with their eyes, (which they heard with their eares) that ſo better meditating and remembring that, which otherwiſe they forget, they might make their hearts as rich in grace, as Sermons (according to the truth of God) are full of goodneſſe: If thou (gentle Reader) meete with any thing in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part of the Sermon, that thou ſhalt iudge worthie the cenſuring, as me right in vnderſtanding me, as I expreſly ſpake it; and let me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vncharitable opinion be ſetled) I pray thee, haue ſome bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly ſignification thereof, and I
<pb facs="tcp:3077:7"/>ſhall be moſt ready (God willing) to ſatisfie thee therein: or to alter, or to better my iudgement, if any man out of the word of God ſhall offer to inſtruct me for as I deſier to teach what I know without grudging; ſo I diſdaine not to learne that, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I am ignorant without bluſhing: we know nothing yet, as we ought to know (ſaith the Apoſtle) therefore I doe not preſume of perfection, I confeſſe much imperfection euery way; and in this do wholy and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſubmit my ſelfe to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church; as I do for my ſinfull life, in Chriſt craue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God. The Lord enforme vs all, with all profitable and conuenient trueth, and frame all our affections thereafter. And the Lord giue vs all grace, to turne our hearts from the world vnto God, our contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into the peace of the Church:
<pb facs="tcp:3077:7"/>and our mindes into loyall obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vnto Soueraigne authority, and our prayers and thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings for our gratious and dread Soueraigne King <hi>IAMES.</hi> Amen, Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3077:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3077:8"/>
            <head>THE LAVER OF THE HEART: OR THE Bath of Sanctification.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IEREM. 4.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>O Ieruſalem, waſh thine heart from wickedneſſe, that thou maieſt be ſaued. (or helped, or kept.)</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He bleſſed Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Hebr. 5.13.14. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pareth the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to the Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of a rich and plentifull houſe-keeper, wherein is laid vp variety of victuals, fit for all perſons and eſtates; both milke for babes, that are vnexpert in the word of righteouſneſſe, and ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger meate for them that are of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per age, which (through long cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3077:9"/>haue their wits exerciſed to diſcerne both good and euill. And our Saurou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt, Matth. 13.52. compareth it to a treaſurie; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are things both new and old, ſo that euery one may receiue hence, what is conuenient for him: new garments, and new veſſels, may bee filled with new wine, &amp; new cloth; and old garments, and old veſſels, may bee filled with old wine, and old cloth, that ſo both may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued together. And to the ſame effect <hi>Haſile</hi> in the firſt Pſalme li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneth the Scripture to a well fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed Apothecaries ſhop, that is ſtored with variety of medecines, for all diſeaſes. And to this end S. <hi>Paul</hi> requireth of <hi>Timothy.</hi> 2.2.15. and of euery Miniſter of the Word, that they ſhew themſelues good worke-men, that need not to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding the word of God aright; not to broach euery truth in euery time and place, leſt ſo they looſe both their labour, and their Auditors,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3077:9"/>while they giue them that, which is good in it ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lfo, but not good for them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>putting new cloth to old gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and make the rent worſe then it was; vnto whom I tying my ſelfe (for counſell) commend this portion of Scripture to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and Chriſtian conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; knowing well that there are none, that ſhall heare mee this day, high, or low; young, or old; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or vnlearned; rich, or poore, of what ſtate and condition ſoeuer, but ought to cauſe his heart to bee exerciſed in the duties of Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Vnto which this Scripture read, ſummoneth vs vnto, euen to walke in, as before God, in this preſent world.</p>
            <p>In the Chapters before going, is laid downe the voluntarie, and cauſeleſſe apoſtaſie of the Iewes, who would not bee kept in the ſtraight waies of God; but fell to Idolatry with falſe gods. And as er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in iudgement breedeth ſinne in the conuerſation: ſo from Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3077:10"/>they turned aſide to the luſts of the Gentiles, as may appeare from the 16. verſ. of the firſt chapter; where the holy Ghoſt expoſtula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the caſe with Iſrael, to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this 4. chapter, preſſeth vpon their conſciences the ſenſe of their ſins, and of the enſuing plague and comming puniſhment, vnto the twelfth verſe. From whence as a Iudge, he paſſeth to a finall and ful ſentence, euen the execution of his full wrath to bee inflicted vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their wickedneſſe; After which, in this verſe read, as in a Pſalme of mercy, hauing ſundry times for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly pronounced them guiltie; the Almighty, heere in the words read, putteth on the affection of a louing Father, in an exhortatiue ſpeech, ſhewing both how they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their liues, and flie from the anger and iudgements to come. Which Scripture (being an infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence depending on the former words, yet a whole ſentence in it ſelfe) in a word containeth, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3077:10"/>with an argument (backing &amp; ſeconding the precept) preſſing ſanctification and holineſſe of life, with the profeſſion of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>Purpoſing then (by the Lords aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, and your godly patience) to ſay ſomething of this matter, let the order, in method, for mee to ſpeak, and you to heare, be the ſelfe ſame, which the holy Ghoſt direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs vnto in the text. If you pleaſe to reade the whole verſe, you ſhall ſee three markable points, punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to offer themſelues to your deepe conſiderations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Commandement.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Argument, which expreſſeth the end, wherefore they ought to ſanctifie.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Exprobration, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iding the Iewes with their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in ſinne, notwithſtanding the great and continuall paines of the Lords Prophets.</p>
            <p>But the words that I haue made choyce of, containing more matter
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3077:11"/>in them, if a skilfull workeman had them in hand, then the time allotted will giue me leaue to vtter (as you haue heard) containe two ſpeciall points.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Firſt, a Commandement.</item>
               <item>2. Secondly, an Argument, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcing the precept.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In the firſt, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight Honourable, Right Worſhipfull, men and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in the Lord beloued;) not I, but the text it ſelfe preſenteth into your view,<note place="margin">1.2.3.</note> three reſpectfull coſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations of waightie conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the Commandement, by way of acclamation, wee are to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the perſons calling, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding &amp; exhorting to ſanctification. Which is God, and the Prophet <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndement was by the hand of the Lord,<note place="margin">2. Chr.
29.25. 1. San. 15.24.</note> and by the hand of his Prophets.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The perſons exhorted, were the people of Ieruſalem.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third is the ſubiect and matter, whereunto they are called.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3077:11"/>
               <hi>O Ieruſalem, waſh, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where fiue things ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be thought vpon.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The affection, expreſſed in the Interiection,
<hi>(O.)</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The voyce, in which God cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vnto them, which is in the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratiue and commanding voice.</item>
               <item>3. The third is the matter, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto they are commanded, which is, to <hi>waſh, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. The fourth is the ſubiect it ſelfe, about what they moſt bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the heart.</item>
               <item>5. The fifth is the obiect, from what they muſt waſh,
<hi>(viz.)</hi> from wickedneſſe.</item>
               <item>6. In the ſecond p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt laying downe the reaſon, wherof one they ought to ſanctifie.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The end of our ſanctification is no leſſe, then our preſeruation in this life, and our ſaluation in the life to come.</p>
            <p>The content and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>here
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ce to this portion of Scripture, may bee read in the words which our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3077:12"/>vſeth, chap. 4.1. (ſaying) <hi>O Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, if thou returne; returne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, ſaith the Lord: and if thou put away thine abomination out of my ſight, then ſhalt thou not remoue.</hi> Or that of
<hi>Moſes,</hi> Deuter. 10.16. <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe therefore the fore-skinne of your heartes, and harden your neckes no more.</hi> Or with <hi>Iſay,</hi> chap. 1. v. 16. <hi>Waſh you, make you cleane, take away the euill of your workes from before mine eyes: ceaſe to doe euill, learne to doe well: for if you conſent and obey, you ſhall eate the good things of the land.</hi> Like vnto this, is that which the holy Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> giueth for doctrine, ſaying, 2. Cor. 7.1. <hi>Seeing then we haue thoſe promiſes, dearely beloued, let vs cleanſe our ſelues from all filthineſſe of the fleſh and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and grow vp vnto full holineſſe in the feare of God.</hi> And if you pleaſe to take notice of the ſcope &amp; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the worde themſelues: in a word, they may thus be read: O Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, of all people in the world moſt beloued; the ioy of my deſires,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3077:12"/>whom I would neither puniſh, nor heare of your plagues: yet becauſe Heb. 4.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> all things lie open and naked to the eyes of God, with whom no vncleane perſon can ſtand iuſtified; I beſeech you in the Lords behalfe: nay the Lord, that in reſpect of thy ſin ſhould bee thy Iudge, is become thy Remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer in the affection of a louing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and that you ſhould not bee amazed with the excellency of his glory, nor confounded with the might of his Maieſty; he hath been pleaſed, in men like to your ſelues, to deliuer vnto you the wonderfull things of God: for if God did not ſend his word, none would aske for it. It it not I therefore that ſpeake vnto you of my owne head: for what am I, but a meſſenger of my ſelfe? It is the Lord that created thee (O Ieruſalem,) that calleth forth of heauen by mee, whom hee hath called, annointed, and aſſigned to be a Prophet vnto you: for none may take this office<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vpon him, but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3077:13"/>he that is called, as <hi>Aaron</hi> was. And ſo much the rather ought you to heede my words, becauſe I ſpeake not of my ſelfe, nor from man, but from God; of whom I haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, both my commiſſion and leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, what, and how to ſpeake, and how farre to proceed againſt you. That you may the rather hearken and giue your attention vnto the words; know the exceeding loue &amp; affection the Lord hath toward you; hee is ſo farre from deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ring your deſtruction, or delighting and pleaſing himſelfe in your poniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as that hee be moneth your miſerie, and lamenteth your loſſe: yea as a compaſſionate father hee pitieth you, and hath compaſſion on all thoſe, of whoſe returne there is any hope. And that you ſhould beleeue it, his will is, that his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers ſhould haue the ſame ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der affection, and compaſſionate care ouer the Church; that
<hi>Iaph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> may be allured to dwell in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ems of <hi>Sam.</hi> And that none may ſtand
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3077:13"/>vp to excuſe himſelfe, my words do not poynt to the Aſſyrions, Idume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns, nor Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bites; but they doe concerne thee (O Ieruſalem, that take your ſelues to bee a purified people,) There be none ſo holy, but need farther information, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; and it is the Miniſters duty to ſpeak the word and rebuke ſinne, and exhort every kinde of profeſſion, vnto religion; and that you the hearers might nor thinke it an Indifferent thing to heare, or not to he are; becauſe men like your ſelues ſpeake it: It is not a counſell, but a commandement, enforcing the eſtimation of the authority of the Prophet, no leſſe the Gods own authority. Wherefore in the Lords behalfe, ſuruey your waits in your he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the glaſſe of Gods law: &amp; you that think your ſelues to bee a ſanctified people, ſhall behold great
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of waſhing, not only the ſeet, but the head alſo; not the out ſide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but the very inſul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is defiled. For I muſt tell you, you are no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3077:14"/>within, then you bee without. But albeit thou art commanded to ſanctifie thy heart, beware of aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming any power vnto your ſelues; for as ſanctification is an action, &amp; not words; ſo it is not mans, but Gods worke, yet ſo, that God wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not vpon man, as vpon ſtocks, but as vpon reaſonable creatures, who by Gods preuenting grace, work together with him the works of God. For in this action, the hand is the whole Trinitie; the water is the teares of repentance;<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.23.</note> the ſoape is the grace of God through Chriſt; and the ſunne that drieth vs, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs accepted, is the applying and iuſtifying faith, through Chriſt Ieſus. And in this worke be ſure, that thou thy ſelfe bee exerciſed therein; for God will not be ſerued and worſhipped by atturneyes, and another for thee: for thou muſt ſerue God for thy ſelfe; becauſe the iuſt man muſt liue by his own faith. And heere, O Ieruſalem, you muſt vnderſtand, although the Lord
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3077:14"/>hath made you the Prince of the Prouinces, ſeating you in the high places, to cleanſe and reforme o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; yet the Lord requireth, that you firſt cleanſe your ſelues, and waſh your owne hearts; before you ſit vpon others, firſt ſit vpon your ſelues. And herein bee not hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, for outward holineſſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the heart goe with it, is abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable before God: but ſanctifie the heart, and all will be cleane. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let the obiect, wherabout you muſt be buſied, be your ſins &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe; for the readieſt way to bring you backe from prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is to conuince your ſelues of ſinne: And ſo doing, the gaine is your owne; for thereby you ſhall not profit the Lord with your righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, but your ſelues. For ſo ſhall you in this life bee preſerued, when others periſh; and in the life to come ſaued, when other ſhall be damned.</p>
            <p>The God of all grace ſo ſanctifie vs in the vnderſtanding hereof ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3077:15"/>that wee ſo apply the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines particularly to our hearts, that all filthineſſe of the fleſh and ſpirit may ſo bee cleanſed, that wee may grow vp vnto full holineſſe in the feare of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Concerning the fuſt point, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Acclamation in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement: where I beſeech you, 1. conſider the perſons ſpeaking, (namely) God by <hi>Ieremie,</hi> and the Prophet in the name of the Lord.<note place="margin">2. Chr.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.25.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And this is of great force to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the commandement.</p>
            <p>The world is become ſo capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that it is more ready to queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by what authority the Preacher preacheth, then with obedience to obey the preaching. Therefore to remoue all lets, that may hinder the acceptance of his doctrine, he firſt of all pleadeth his commiſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> From whence wee may learne, that none ought to ſpeake &amp; teach in the Lords name, that be not able to ſhew their authority and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to bee ſet on worke, both
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3077:15"/>by God and his Church.</p>
            <p>This the Prophet proueth, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king not in his owne, but in the Lords name. As (if he ſhould haue ſaid,) I doe not of my ſelfe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you might think me too buſie; but I haue authority and commiſſion diuine, and am ſet a worke by the Lord, whoſe will I muſt obey; and therfore you ought to heare me with patience.</p>
            <p>For I am none of thoſe who run, and God hath not ſent; my calling is from God. And for this cauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued I the anoynting,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.21.</note> which is nothing elſe but the aſſignement, vocation, and ordination of any, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n office in Church or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, with a promiſe of beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſit gifts for the diſcharge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. To this end, Kings, Prophets, &amp; Prieſts in the old Teſtament were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nnointed; ſignifying the ſpirituall oyle of Gods grace, fitting vs to our calling: this is that <hi>Chryſma,</hi> that will teach vs all things.</p>
            <p>Here I mind not with <hi>Ire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 3. cap.
3.</note>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:3077:16"/>to ſhew you, that <hi>Alia vocatio eſt extraordinaria, &amp; alia ordinaria:</hi> that the one is without the ſuffrage of men, by the onely voice of God, as was <hi>Abraham, Moſes,</hi> and the Prophets vnder the Law; and as <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> and the Apoſtles in the time of the Goſpell: and that the other was by the ſuffrage of the Church, <hi>Precibus &amp; impoſitione manuum;</hi> as now in the time of the Goſpell the Lord ſendeth labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers into his vineyard: But my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is briefly to ſhew you, that none without a lawfull calling fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Church (by whoſe hands the Lord ſendeth forth fit men into the Miniſtery) ought to be heard of the Lords people.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> If the Lord would not beare with any, of what degree ſoeuer, in the time of the Law, but would puniſh euen Kings, that would meddle with the Prieſts office, that had no calling thereunto.</p>
            <p>Then none (without a lawful cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) may take vpon them the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3077:16"/>not bee heard of the Lords people.</p>
            <p>But the propoſition is true, Exod. 28.1. Numb. 16.32.35. 1. Sam.
13.9.10.11.13. 2. Reg. 9.7.31. 2. Sam. 6.6.7. 2. Reg. 15.5.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> If no man may take this office but he that is called, as <hi>Aaron</hi> was, Then, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But, Hebr. 5.4.</p>
            <p>If the Lord from heauen com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth of ſuch, that runne before they be ſent; then ſuch ought not to bee heard of the Lords people. But the Lord complaineth, let. 23.21. ſaying: <hi>I haue not ſent theſe Prophets, yet they runne: I haue not ſpoken vnto them, and yet they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If Chriſt Ieſus in the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment approueth this; then ſuch ought not to bee heard, that haue not the ſame approbation.</p>
            <p>But Chriſt Ieſus from heauen in the choſen veſſell Saint
<hi>Paul,</hi> Acts 9.12. ſending him to <hi>Ananias,</hi> that hee might lay his hands vpon him,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3077:17"/>and receiue ſight: <hi>Vrim</hi> and
<hi>Thum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mim,</hi> ſcience and good conſcience: knowledge, and holineſſe to beare his name before the Gentiles, which maketh the propoſition. If in nature, order doe ſound againſt ſuch irregular perſons; then it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be well pleaſing to God, that any in the Lords name, without the Lords appointment, ſhould med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with the Ephod, or deale with the ſacred things of God.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> vpon the 1. of Sam. 14. ſaith,
<hi>Spectanda eſt in eccleſiaſticis Eutaxia, in politicis autem parendum eſt.</hi> In Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call lawes, good order muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered; but in politicall, wee muſt obey. And to thruſt in a mans ſelfe without an aſſignement, is againſt order, which is ingrauen in euery mans perſon, euen from the head to the foote. For is not the head a tower; the eyes watchmen, the eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lids windowes for light; the mouth a doore to let in prouiſion; the tongue a ſpeaker, to call for that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3077:17"/>which is needfull, and to examine that which is doubtfull: be not the cares ſpies to liſten; the hands ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitors; the feet meſſengers, to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and recarrie;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>al</note> the teeth grinders of natures prouiſion? is not the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat a taſter, &amp; the ſtomack a kitchin, wherein all things bee prepared for the benefit of nature; that ſo the whole body bee preſerued as the cloſet of the ſoule. All which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing held in that order, that God hath ſet them, doe cry againſt the diſordered furie of men in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie, that runne before they are ſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Yea, not onely Diuinity, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and nature, but Chriſtian po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie, proclaimeth, that if Iudget, &amp; Ieſtic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in their Seſſions, ſuting for correction of vice, in the Kings name firſt plead their commiſſion; then ought no man in the name of the King of heauen preach, without his aſſignement.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For application, It ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rueth to teach vs, that as many
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue any feare of God, ought to heare with
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3077:18"/>all meekneſſe. Such Miniſters and meſſengers of the Lord, that haue receiued their calling from the Church, which is that which Saint <hi>Iames</hi> giueth for doctrine;<note place="margin">Iom. 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>Wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called, bee the Lords ſeruants, therefore wee muſt doe our maſters meſſage:</hi> and hee that doth but his maſters meſſage &amp; no more, ought not to be blamed; nay ought to be beleeued. For whatſoeuer the Lord by his meſſengers ſayeth, muſt bee beleeued; and being commanded by them, who are firſt commanded by the Lord, they muſt be obeyed. Therefore the Lord in this our text commanding high and low, rich &amp; poore, to ſanctifie themſelues, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vnto vs here preſent. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this day wee ought to obey this commaundement, as we will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere it at our vttermoſt perill.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> The ſecond vſe ſerueth for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooſe, firſt concerning the Papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, whoſe vocation is ſcarce ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to giue them a lawfull aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to bee Miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3077:18"/>and of the Sacraments. For the right of thoſe orders, whereby they were ordained to ſacrifice for the quicke and the dead, vndermining the ſacrifice of our Sauiour, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie to be one and the ſame with the moſt iuſt and equall lawes, which the Lord made touching the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of vocation.</p>
            <p>The third vſe; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Yea this laſtly ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to teach vs, to confute &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the irregular and prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous courſe of the Separatiſts, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, and Familiſts, that runne before they are ſent; and take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to ordaine and ſend forth Miniſters, being no Miniſters them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Wherefore ſuch as go forth without the ordinance of the Church, (as Heretickes, and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matickes doe) are not to bee recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, nor heard of ſuch as feare God. For what truth may hee deliuer from God, that hath his calling fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man, and not from God? what Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments may hee adminiſter, that hath no lawfull calling to the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3077:19"/>what profit may he bring vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the people, himſelfe not brought vp, nor ſent of God? euen as much as Saint
<hi>Peter,</hi> that fiſhed on the wrong ſide of the ſhip al night, and caught nothing: ſo much good, and no more may we looke to come by their miniſterie, that in contempt of the Churches ordination, and impoſition of hands, runne vp and downe, gathering vnto themſelues a heape of hearers, who are not taught (as you haue heard) from God, by <hi>Ieremy;</hi> but from
<hi>Ieremy;</hi> by <hi>Ieremy,</hi> and ſo doe, <hi>Toto coelo, errare à coelo;</hi> feed vpon mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, in ſtead of the immortall food of Gods word. Hence it commeth, that diuines turne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion into diſputation, and ſtand more vpon ſcience then good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to get themſelues a name, by leading the poore people into a thouſand pitifull opinions.</p>
            <p>In the firſt and beſt daies of the Church it was farre otherwife, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which glorious dayes the Lord
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3077:19"/>Ieſus brings vs, and that ſoone, leſt Chriſtians turne Iewes, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity be turned into Atheiſme; and let euery good Chriſtian ſay, Amen.</p>
            <p>Now a word,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> as they bee the words of the Prophet, in the name of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ieremiah</hi> ſpeaketh from the Lord; Therefore of God hee muſt learne his dutie.</p>
            <p>From whence, I beſeech you, Fathers and brethren, let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme our iudgements, that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God are not before hand to bee taught their leſſons of men; but they muſt firſt learne both mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and manner, what to ſpeak, and how to ſpeake from God, before they teach men. The truth of this, our example leadeth vs to. For <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy</hi> ſpeaketh from God, and not from man.</p>
            <p>This doctrine runneth with the current and ſtreame of the liuely waters, Exod. 3.12. The Lord ſaid to <hi>Moſes, I will bee with thee:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 4.12.</note> 
               <hi>and I
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3077:20"/>will be with thy mouth, and will teach thee what thou ſhalt ſay.</hi> Of the Iudges of Iſrael it was ſaid,<note place="margin">Iudg. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>And the ſpirit of the Lord came vpon him, and he iudged Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the Lords appointment,<note place="margin">Iſa. 6.6.</note> with a coale from his Altar, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame the tongue of his meſſenger.</p>
            <p>Becauſe to whom a Miniſter is to performe his dutie, of him hee is to learne his dutie.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.17.</note> But in teaching of men, a Miniſter is to performe his duty to God. 1. Cor. 4.1. &amp; 3.10.</p>
            <p>Therefore wee muſt not ſpeake what we will, nor how wee liſt; but all muſt be both for matter &amp; man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as God will. So ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, 1. Reg. 22.14. <hi>Whatſoeuer the Lord ſaith vnto me, that will I ſpeak.</hi> Yea ſo ſaith the falſe Prophet, Numb. 23.3.
<hi>Whatſoeuer the Lord ſheweth vnto me, I will tell thee.</hi> And this is that which the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> prophecied of our bleſſed Sauiour, that before he ſhould be ſent forth of the Father to preach; it was ſaid,<note place="margin">Luk. 4.18.</note> that <hi>the ſpirit of the Lord God is vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3077:20"/>me, therefore hath the Lordan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed me, he hath ſent me to preach good tidings, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude this: If ſome Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates will ſcorne to learne of the Diuine, to pronounce iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at the barre, why ſhould the Diuine, by mans directions, bee taught to ſpeake in the Pulpit? If the Captaine muſt not ſight, when the meane ſouldier will appoint him; nor the ſouldier fight with ſuch weapons as his enemies will appoint him; then Gods Miniſters ought not to teach, what the beſt man in the pariſh will appoint him. But the propoſition is true: <hi>Ergo,</hi> wofull it is to heare, how the gold of the Sanctuarie is changed,<note place="margin">Ierem. Lam.
4.1.2.</note> and become dim; and how the Noble men of Sion, comparable to fine gold, are become earthen pitchers, waiting on the humour of men, to be filled with winde, that they may fill others with vanity: that the Lord may ſay now, as this Prophet ſaid of Iudah, and Iſrael, Lam. 2.14.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3077:21"/>
               <hi>Thy Prophets haue looked out vaine and fooliſh things for thee, and they haue not diſcouered thine iniquitie, to turne away thy captiuity, but haue looked out for falſe prophecies, and cauſes of baniſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vſe is both for reprehenſion, and for inſtruction: firſt, for repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, it reproueth, firſt ſuch Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, that bee ſlaues and vaſſals to mens affections. Such were the foure hundred, (1. Reg. 22.6.) Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, to pleaſe <hi>Ahab.</hi> And would to God there were not among the Prophets, that will ſpeak, as the beſt man of the pariſh will haue him ſpeake; and that will ſpeake mans inuentious in painted eloquence, to ſet forth themſelues; and that there were not, that becauſe they may not ſpeake what they will, ſpeake not at all, making a diuorce betweene the tongue, and the hart, leſt their Poperie be ſeene. 1. Cor. 7.23. Galath. 1.10. 1. Theſſal. 2.4.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it reproueth ſuch that teach for the doctrines of Gods

<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3077:21"/>commandements; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Mans precepts, ſetting forth their owne inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and their <hi>(Traditiones ſancta Romana)</hi> with more authority and commendation, then the word of God. Maith. 15.9. becauſe if men or Angels proach otherwiſe, then wee haue receiued from Chriſt and his Apoſtles, they bee accurſed. <hi>Anathama marah natha.</hi> Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to which doctrine of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle Saint
<hi>Paul,</hi> Galath. 1.9. <hi>Cyp. ad Powp. p.</hi> 228. faith: <hi>Nihil inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netur niſi quod tradit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n eſt: vnde eſt iſtae traditio, vtrum de dominica &amp; Euangelica authoritate deſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, an de Apoſtolorum mand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is at ques Epiſtolis veniens; ca eni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>da
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe qua ſcripta ſunt, &amp;c.</hi> and propoſed vnto <hi>Ioſuah,</hi> ſaying. <hi>Let not the booke of the Law depart from thy mouth.</hi> Vntill I deeply weighed this, I was drowned in the opinion of learning, reſolued that where learning is, there is the light of true vnderſtanding; till together with
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3077:22"/>this (I ſay) I called to minde, that the Scribes and Phariſees, chiefe Doctors, experienced in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, vnderſtood not the Law, nor Chriſts parables aright, becauſe to them it was not giuen, Matth. 13.1. Luk. 10.21. but was giuen to babes. Whereupon I am now moued to ſay, it is not the wiſe dome of fleſh and blood, that can iudge of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; not learning, but God enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tening, that directeth the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to the right obiect. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I praiſe that illuſtrious
<hi>Scali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, exere,</hi> 359. who ſaith, <hi>Nostra hac in literarum ſtudijs peregrinatio, ſine ſuprema Luce, miſerabilia qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam erratio eſt.</hi> This our painfull peregrination in ſtudies, if it be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of that ſupreame light, in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a miſerable kinde of wandring. Yet in giuing this glory to God, I commend not certaine ſpeculatiue ſpirits, that runne in the other extreame, who thinke God will make knowne his myſteries to them, whether they take paines or
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3077:22"/>no. For if the prouiſion of this ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer life cannot bee gotten without the ſweat of our browes; much leſſe can the food of that better life bee gained without the ſweat, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious ſearching of our ſoules. But to returne to humane traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, from whence we haue digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: In ſpeaking of humane lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, I beſeech you to vnderſtand me, and that with diſtinction; For whan I name humane inuentions, &amp; traditions, whether of doctrines, or of ceremonies, I pray rightly to be vnderſtood. For concerning do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, I meane not, that it is vtterly vnlawfull to mention men, &amp; mens writings in the place of God in preaching: for it is lawfull to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage in Sermons the authority of men, making for the truth of God, as it was lawfull for <hi>Dauid</hi> to kill
<hi>Goliah</hi> with his owne ſword. For an arrow out of a mans owne qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer againſt himſelfe, doth more fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the wound, and wound him to death, then the ſword of his enemy.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:3077:23"/>
            <p>And concerning humane lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, I ſay with Saint <hi>Baſil Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potes,</hi> that both the knowledge and vſe of naturall learning in a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is lawfull, and ſomtimes neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie: and this doth the very exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Apoſtle reach vs, Act. 17.28. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to conuince the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and idolatrous Athenians of great blockiſhnes, and propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, alleageth the ſaying of <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> the Poet, to proue the true God; who ſaid,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.33.</note> that in God wee had our liuing, our mouing, and being. And in the queſtion of the reſurrection, reprouing the Epicures, who as if there were no reſurrection, nor life to come, gaue themſelues to all pleaſure, and riotouſneſte of life, S. <hi>Paul</hi> condemned by a ſentence out of <hi>Menander</hi> the Poet, ſaying; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill ſpeech corrupt good manners. The like he alleaged out of
<hi>Epime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nides,</hi> Tit. 1.12. ſaying, the Creti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are alwaies liars. Thus wee ſee not onely humane, but prophane learning may ſerue Diuinicy: as

<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3077:23"/>hand-maidens, being purified and cleanſed from the Idolatrie, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety of the Heathen. Thus farre I dare goe, albeit I dare not ſpeake with the ſpirit of Atheiſme, and blaſphemie, that
<hi>Plinies</hi> Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie equalleth the bookes of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes:</hi> not that <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Ethickes, and Politickes, equall the Proverbs of
<hi>Salomon:</hi> nor that <hi>Mareus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relius,</hi> equalleth <hi>Marke</hi> the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt: nor that <hi>Merlius</hi> prophecy be one with the Prophecie of <hi>Iſay:</hi> nor the eloquence of <hi>Cicero,</hi> and
<hi>Demeſthenes,</hi> equall the cloque noe of the holy Ghoſt: nor any Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors or Fathers, before the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or Chriſt: much leſſe the Pope and his decrees, to be before, or equall with, the decrees of God in the Bible. Neither doe I meane of traditions concerning ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, that it is vtterly vnlawfull to vſe any in the Church-apparell and ſeruice, being commanded by the Chriſtian Magiſtrate. For as religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on can ſtand without Popiſh traſh
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3077:24"/>from Rome, and Rhemes: yet
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> religion neuer was without certain ceremonies; euen as a learned Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturer of Geneua hath ſaid,<note place="margin">Bucer in Mat 18.</note> that <hi>Cerep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oniae enim testes religiouis ſunt:</hi> Ceremonies are witneſſes of religion; for there are religious, as well as irreligious ceremonies. Can Baptiſme bee without water, and the Lords Supper without bread and wine? bee not prayers perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with kneeling; and what let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Sacrament to bee receiued kneeling, when the words (deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering the ſame into the hands of the people) it nothing elſe but a prayer; and the preciſeſt (I hope) will not denie kneeling at prayer. The Scripture ſoundeth as forth of a Trumpet, that indifferent things, and ceremonies of time, place and perſons bee not vtterly vnlawfull. Wherefore, deare brethren, ſtand not vpon titles; for they which la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour well, are worthie of double honour: regard not garments, for <hi>Iuſtin</hi> the <hi>Martyr</hi> would put on a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3077:24"/>heatheniſh garment, rather then he would leaue preaching of Chriſt. Yea S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe, rather then there ſhould bee any let to the preaching of the Goſpell, hee would make bald the head, and ſhaue the haire.<note place="margin">Act. 18.18.</note> And therefore woe vnto vs, that liue in theſe degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate dayes, that for blacke &amp; white, round and ſquare, will ſuffer our ſelues (the Elders of the daughters of Sion) to ſit vpon the ground, and keepe ſilence; that leaue our preaching, our maintenance, and care of our families, wanting more the ſupply of our wants, then the people want vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Now a word for inſtruction out of this doctrine; whence, ſith Miniſters ought to ſpeake from the Lord and to learne their duties of God, wee may learne, that euery Miniſter of the Lord approued, muſt ſpeake with the euidence of Gods ſpirit, without adding,<note place="margin">Deut. 4.2.</note> or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhing. 1. Corinth. 2.4. Neither ſtood my preaching in the entice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3077:25"/>ſpeech of mans wiſedome, but in plaine euidence of the ſpirit (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul.</hi>) 2. Cor. 2.17. We are not as thoſe many, that make mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize of the word of God. Micah. 3.8. For the Miniſter of God ought to be full of the power of the ſpirit of the Lord, and of iudgement, and of ſtrength, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare vnto <hi>Iacob</hi> his tranſgreſſion, and to Iſrael his ſin. Much might be ſaid in this point; but I feare I haue dwelt too long vpon the firſt branch; I meane the perſons ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, ſo that time will not tarrie for me. Therefore (with your pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) I paſſe to the perſons exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or called vpon.</p>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>The ſecond branch in the firſt part.</head>
               <p>The perſons ſpoken to, is the daughter of <hi>Iudah,</hi> the Prince of the Prouinces; and of Cities, Ieruſalem, the moſt glorious of all the world?</p>
               <p>The former Chapter exhorted Iſrael, and the ten Tribes to repent,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3077:25"/>who for their ſinnes were carried into Aſſyria, in the ninth yeere of <hi>Hoſea,</hi> King of the ten Tribes.</p>
               <p>So in this Chapter, Iudah is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon to cleanſe his waies, and amend his life, leſt the like euill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall him, that ouertooke his brother Iſrael.</p>
               <p>Now concerning Iudah, which was the onely people of God, and ſo inſtructed by his Prophets, as none were more, nor ſo much as the people of Ieruſalem: yet heere they needed further to bee called vpon.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> It ſerueth to teach vs, that there be none ſo learned, ſo wiſe, ſo reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, nor ſo holy in this world; but need further reformation, and ſtill to bee called vpon, and put in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance by the Lords ſeruants, for an encreaſe in the growth of grace, proued heere. Ieruſalem (as this famous City of our kingdome) was the ſchoole of the Prophets; a place eminent for learning, renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for religion; yet muſt be more
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3077:26"/>religious: as the Zaphire for ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, yet need to bee cleanſed. Therefore in this life is no perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but a growth in godlineſſe is here continually looked for of God at our hands. 1. Pet.
2.2. <hi>As new borne babes deſire</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.<note place="margin">Deut. 6.7. Num. 15.38. Deut. 11.18.</note> 
                  <hi>the ſincere milke of the Word, that you may grow therby:</hi> For this cauſe the Prophet
<hi>Dauid</hi> knew it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for vs to chew the cud, and to whet Gods word vpon our harts, to giue an edge to that which hath been taught vs, Pſal. 12. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſaith: The bleſſed man will meditate vpon the Law of the Lord day and night. And to this end Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> 2.1.4.5. calleth vpon the well taught Iewes, to ioyn vertue with vertue, &amp;c. And S.
<hi>Iude,</hi> verſ. 5. telleth vs, it is needfull to be better inſtructed, and to bee put in minde of that which we do know.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. Becauſe naturally, wee are forgetfull of the things wee haue learned.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Becauſe our daily ſinnes doe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3077:26"/>eclipſe and ſtraiten Gods graces in vs,<note place="margin">Iſa. 59.2. Ierem. 5.25.</note> ſo that the ſpirit is not as in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Becauſe there be none ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but by Satans ſubtiltie may fall from the good begun. 1. Cor. 10.12. <hi>Hee that ſtandeth, take heede leſt he fall.</hi> Rom. 11.20.
<hi>Thouſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt by faith, be not high minded, but feare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> 1. The vſe of this doctrine may informe our iudgements, that there was neuer any, nor may bee any (pure or perfect) in this life, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne: but that the perfection of the Saints is alwaies here further to bee informed for knowledge; and more and more to grow vp in ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification of the fleſh,<note place="margin">2. Cor.
7.1.</note> and ſpirit. For what is he among the ſonnes of <hi>Adam.</hi> Prou. 20.9. that can ſay, his heart is cleane from ſinne.<note place="margin">Iob 9.30.</note> The very clothes we put on (ſaith <hi>Iob</hi>) make vs filthie. Know (Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable) that our perfection, is to know our imperfections. Yet I am not ignorant, that there is a genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3077:27"/>that are pure in their owne conceit,<note place="margin">Pro. 30.12.</note> and yet are not waſhed from their filthineſſe. But I ſay with the ancient,<note place="margin">Aug. conf. l.
9. c. 13</note> 
                  <hi>Vae etiam laudabile vitae hominum, ſiremota miſericordia diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutias eam.</hi> Woe to our very praiers and preachings, if they be examined without mercy.</p>
               <p>The ſecond vſe ſerueth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue ſuch, that thinke, if they haue heard Gods word, for ſome ſmall time, and from thence haue attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto ſome ciuill carriage, and a varniſhed profeſſion; that then they haue learned enough. But this is falſe; for wee muſt encreaſe: for it is not enough that the corne bee a blade, but that it be an care, &amp; that it be cone full flowred: and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians muſt neuer giue ouer, till our righteouſneſſe breake forth as the perfect day.</p>
               <p>The third vſe directeth vs vnto watchfulneſſe ouer our conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and ſheweth, that we cannot be too forward, as prophane Atheiſts ſay: becauſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> life is but a grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3077:27"/>age; and therefore <hi>non progre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de,</hi> is, <hi>regredi,</hi> not to goe forward, is to goe backward. Wherefore I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, take the Apoſtles coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and worke forth your ſaluation in feare and trembling.<note place="margin">Phil. 2.12. Prou. 28
1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.1. Pet. 1.17.</note> For bleſſed is the man that feareth alwaies. And let vs that cal God Father, paſſe our time in feare and trembling. 1. Ioh. 4.14. 1. Cor. 4.34.</p>
               <p>But heere with <hi>Heraclitus,</hi> wee haue luſt cauſe to weepe; and with <hi>Ier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>y,</hi> to let teares runne downe night and day, for the ſinnes of our conuerſation, which makes ioy in bell, and reioycing among the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in earth. Which is that, that <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> ſaith, cauſed
<hi>Tacitus</hi> ſo to raile againſt Chriſtians, that the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans committed thoſe crimes that the Heathens abhorred. Were <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus</hi> aliue at this day, hee ſhould ſee ſome (called Chriſtians) out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dare the diuels themſelues, in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. For the diuels beleeue that there is a God, and tremble at it: but wee may heare ſome, that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3077:28"/>name the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues Chriſtians, auouch, that there is no God, and laugh at it. I beſeech you (Right Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) open your eyes, and looke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you, and you ſhall ſee ſinnes inuented as faſt as faſhions. I warne you of theſe things, and beſeech you, to take fall hold of iudgment, which is <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſtaffe, and our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignes Scepter, by which, you that are Iudges, beare rule vnder him; that ſo both the iudiciall, and iniudiciall of you, in this honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble City, may liue better, and walke with your God. So ſhall your names flouriſh on earth, and your ſoules raigne in heauen; while o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers rot in the graue, and liue in torment in hell.</p>
               <p>Thus (beloued) from the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the fall of Ieruſalem, (Gods deare children) and of the chiefeſt in place; let vs, firſt, humble our ſelues before God, and not wax proud of any thing. For hee that ſtandeth, may fall.</p>
               <p>And ſith the moſt excellent bee
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3077:28"/>ſubiect to infirmitie, let vs bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muniſhed of the many fraikies, that lie hid in vs, and which, through hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, we cannot ſee. And from benee bee more charitable, and not ſo cenſorious of other; but to bee more temperate, conſidering wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto wee our ſelues are ſubiect to be tempted.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>4</label> Againe, in that hee crieth vnto Ieruſalem, both generally, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly; indefinitely to all, and in particular, to euery one, as well as to any one.</p>
               <p>It ſerueth to teach vs, that the dutie of the Miniſter is, to ſpeake the word to all, and to rebuke ſinne in all, and to exhort euery kinde of profeſſion vnto religion: the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the Nobles; the rich, the pooke, the Artificers, Seruing-men, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, Merchants, Tradeſ-men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as well the ſhop-keeper, as the Vintner; as well the Maſter, as the Apprentice, muſt bee ſpoken vnto, exhorted, and rebuked by the Peeacher. Which is that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3077:29"/>ſetteth downe for doctrine,<note place="margin">Act. 20.3.</note> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>I ceaſed not to warne euery one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. Becauſe they to whom ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doth belong, to them doth Gods word, and the miniſterie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long.</p>
               <p>But it belongeth to all ſorts of people.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.4. Act. 20.31.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. It the Miniſter muſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor to be free from all mens blood; then they muſt lay Gods word to euery mans conſcience. But they muſt labour to bee free from the blood of all men. Act. 20.26. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Gods Miniſters muſt not fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e any mans perſon, nor ſpare any mans profeſſion teacher, nor hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer; Prince, nor people; ruler, nor ſubiect; rich, nor poore, &amp;c. For the blood of the poore will ſtaine, as well as of the rich. O this ſhould make both Miniſter &amp; people trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when they heare that the blood of men ſhall bee required at their hands. The ſteward ſhall anſwere for his maſters goods; the Factor,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3077:29"/>for his maſters money; the ſcholer for his learning: and ſhall not the Paſtor anſwere for the ſinne of the people? If our commuſſion muſt ſtretch it ſelfe as farre as Chriſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption; then our miniſtery muſt bee to all:<note place="margin">1. Tim.
2.4.</note> but the propoſition is true. Therefore to all in generall, and to euery ſort, and condition, &amp; ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. For wee muſt make our mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery to be like Chriſts net, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Mat. 13.1.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The vſe teacheth, that ſith all muſt be ſpoken vnto, the Miniſters muſt not flatter the people, nor conceale the iudgement of God from their ſinnes. For,<note place="margin">Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 24.24. Ezech. 13.4.5. 10.11.1. Cor.
14.24.</note> 
                  <hi>He that ſaith to the wicked, thou art righteous, him ſhall the people curſe, and the multitude ſhall abhorre him.</hi> But if we tell euery man of his ſinne, then he that beleeueth, as well as he that beleeueth not; and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> learned, as well as the vnlearned, is rebuked of all men, and iudged of all. Heere let me exhort, and bee exhorted. For what is any, that wee ſhould feare? they bee but men in nature, and ſo
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3077:30"/>are we; and they bee but mortall, as well as we; and they ſhall come to iudgement, as well as we. Let ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore both Preacher, &amp; hearer iudge themſelues, that they be not iudged of the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label>
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. But heere is offered iuſt cauſe to reproue thoſe, that reproue the Reprouer. For nothing more cutteth the throat of reprehenſion, then to rebuke him that reproueth. Which moued <hi>Hoſea,</hi> 4.4. to ſay, <hi>Let none rebuke nor reproue ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for the people are as they, that rebuke the Prieſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the ſin (I am ſure) of the countrey: bleſſed is this City, if it be not guiltie hereof. But are there not among vs, that will teach wiſe men, themſelues being fooles; that will controll learned men, themſelues being ignorant; that wil ſchoole Preachers, &amp; yet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues will not heare; that will rule Magiſtrates, themſelues being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and will not obey; that will ſeeme to doe all things, themſelues
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3077:30"/>not able to doe any thing, but that which is euill: Ierem. 9.3. <hi>For they are ſtrong to euill: but they haue no courage for the truth.</hi> But I muſt be briefe: for time calleth to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect in hand, and to preſſe the point expreſſing the matter, whereunto they are commanded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>The third part.</head>
               <p>In the matter laying downe the third general point, fiue things may be obſerued.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the affection, expreſſed in the interiection
<hi>(O)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, the voyce in which God calleth vnto them, which is Imperatiue, and not obſecratiue.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the matter it ſelfe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto they are commanded, which is to <hi>waſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, the fourth is the ſubiect, which they muſt waſh, which is <hi>the heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, the fifth is the obiect, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout which they muſt be buſied, or
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3077:31"/>from what they muſt waſh their hearts, which is, <hi>from wickednes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt concerning the affection, <hi>O Ieruſalem;</hi> which both concerneth God and the Prophet. And firſt as it concerneth God, it is a word of great affection: and a word of moſt euident demonſtration, and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of Gods vnwillingneſſe to puniſh, and of his ready inclination to ſhew mercie.</p>
               <p>From whence the inſtruction to vs is,<note place="margin">1</note> that God taketh no delight in puniſhing the ſonnes of men, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued here in the voyce of pitie and compaſſion,<note place="margin">Pſal 81 13. Ierem. Lamen. 3.33.</note> as it were, bewailing their eſtate fallen into, by ſinne. If parents haue no delight, but griefe, in puniſhing their children; then God taketh no delight in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſonnes of men.</p>
               <p>But, 2. Sam. 18.33. and the Lord himſelfe ſaith, Ezek.
18.23. he hath no deſire that the wicked ſhould dye: 32. neither doth he delight in the death of the ſinner. If God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth our repentance; then hee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3077:31"/>no delight in puniſhing.</p>
               <p>But, Ezek. 18.21. and 33.11. Luke 13.34. Therefore, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If in God, to bee angrie and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſinners be not a proper worke of Gods nature, but an improper and ſtrange worke of God; Then God taketh no delight in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſonnes of men.</p>
               <p>But, Exod. 34.6. Iſai. 28.21. <hi>For the Lord ſhall ſtand as in mount Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>razim: he ſhall bee wroth as in the valley of Gibeon, that he may doe his worke, his ſtrange worke, and bring to paſſe his act, his ſtrange act.</hi> Thus you may ſee, it is the proper worke of Gods nature to ſhew mercie: but his improper worke to puniſh: It is naturall to God to be gratious, but to him it is a ſtrange and an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall work to delight in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if I may ſo ſay. God puniſheth, as Carpenters pull downe ruinous houſes, that is, to build them vp bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then they were before; ſo doth the Lord take vs of there, &amp; down here, that he may build vs on high.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:3077:32"/>
               <p n="1">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. The vſe ſerueth to teach vs to abhorre their prophaneneſſe, that vnder the continuance of any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like or particular afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (as now, in this long continued drought) doe ſay, that God ſporteth himſelfe in puniſhing the world: know, I beſeech you in the feare of God, that God is delighted, and taketh pleaſure to exerciſe his mercie, and hath compaſſion vpon all thoſe, of whoſe returne there is any hope.<note place="margin">Luk. 15.4.</note> He is to farre from ſporting himſelf at our miſerie, that contrarily, as a carefull father, he ſeeketh vs vp, he goeth after vs till he hath found vs; he ſtaieth not till wee returne, but preuenteth vs with his grace: and albeit grace in vs is imperfect, and moueth a farre off,<note place="margin">Luk. 15.10.</note> verſ. 10. God in compaſſion ſeeketh vs, till he hath found vs; and then leadeth vs with the cords of a man,<note place="margin">Oſca 11 4.</note> euen with the bands of loue: for he calleth vs by his Preachers; draweth vs by his ſpirit;<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.19.</note> wooeth vs by his benefits, that he may pardon vs in his mercy,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3077:32"/>and in loue receiue vs to glorie. Pſal.
103.9.13. For our God is an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lluring God.<note place="margin">Cant. 5.2.</note> Gen. 9.27. he ſhall allure <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pheth</hi> to dwell in the tents of <hi>Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here me thinks, I he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e ſome politike Proteſtant of eſtate
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt in heart) ſay: If the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e thus full of compaſſion, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e by all meane a ſinners, and ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> goe aſtray from him; on where is that compaſſion, and when will this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luring courſe: bee taken with the Papiſts, that they might heare of the ſame? To whom I anſwere, as S.
<hi>Paul</hi> doth in the like caſe, Rom. 10.18. I demaund, haue they not heard? yea they haue been merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deale with by our late Queene of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> memorie: and they haue been lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>gly intreated by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie; and curteouſly perſwaded by their brethren; to tread in the Kings high way. But all in vaine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which ſheweth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> an vnion of religious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> harder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hing to effect;
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n vnion of kingdomes. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:3077:33"/>it vpon my ſoules altar, that thee man would merit eternitie, that could reconcile the long ſeuered Papiſts and Proteſtants. But it is in vaine to aſſaie it: for the Ancients haue concluded, that, <hi>null<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>t as fidei,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyp. ep.</hi> 55. 2. Cor. 6 14.15.</note>
                  <hi>&amp; perfidia poteſt,</hi> God and B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial can neuer agree. Yet if I might obtaine my requeſt at the hands of God, my prayer for my Countrie ſhould bee: that religion may bee once purged from the lees of the Romane grape, that ſo euery thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſoule might drinke out of the fountaine of the written word of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third vſe confirmeth our iudgements for our comfort, that the Lord will not deale with vs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our deſerts, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his mercies in Ieſus Chriſt. For Chriſt Ieſus alone fulfilled the Law for vs,<note place="margin">Iſai. 73.4.5.</note> and ſuffered our puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for he did be are our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and carried our ſorrowes: hee was wounded for our tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, broken for our iniquities: the ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3077:33"/>of our peace was vpon him, and with his ſtripes wee are healed. And this is the Chriſtians triumph, that the partition wall is broken downe, and the hand-wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting faſtened to the Croſſe, and all our ſinnes ſhall not be able to rar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier vp the gate of Gods mercies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them that beleeue.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The fourth vſe from this, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe to mercie in God, checketh the vncharitable practiſes of three ſorts of perſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt the Papiſts, whoſe hearts be infected with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blood-crying and heauen pearcing ſinne, <hi>Occide, imò manduca hareticum;</hi> that tip their fingers of a ſanguine colour in the blood of thoſe men, who doe but tranſgreſſe the vnwritten vntruths of their ſcarlet Pope: and in the meane time, crie out of the want of charitie amongſt Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it reproueth the raſh and inconſiderate courſe, as farre from charitie, as from wiſedome; deliuering the members of Chriſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3077:34"/>to Satan, and that for a trifle; when as thoſe that are ſpirituall,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.1</note> ought to raiſe ſuch that fall, with the ſpirit of meekneſſe, conſidering themſelues, leſt they alſo be tempted.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, it reproueth the furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpirits of the Browniſts, who for blemiſhes, (when themſelues are moſt filthie) caſt out our whole Church, for no apparant Church of God; yet who is he, that in many things ſinneth not?</p>
               <p>The God of heauen cleere our eyes,<note place="margin">Leuit. 19
17. Prou. 27 6. Gal. 6.1</note> and rectifie our iudgements; that in cenſuring ſinne in all men, we may iudge charitably of all, till we ſee the end of all.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The fifth vſe. And now glue me leaue to ſpeak to you (right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and reuerend Fathers) for Gods example here, ſpeaketh aloud to you my Lord, and lieth at the doores of the Magiſtracie, who are to execute iuſtice in the gate: yea the fatherleſſe, the widow, and the orphant doth crie: the Maſter and the apprentice doe call vpon you:
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3077:34"/>rich and the poore doe call: you the priſons, and thoſe that are bound in chaines and iron, doe crie vnto you that be in authoritie, to imit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te the Lord of heauen and earth: be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, as hee is mercifull put on the bowels of compaſſion in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: cenſure and iudge your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, the Lords people, with all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morce and pitie: take no pleaſure in puniſhing taunt not thoſe whom the Lord hath brought before you: delight not to defame not diſgrace thoſe, whom God Almightie hath put in your hands to correct: bee not like the Philiſtims, laugh not at the ſorrowes of
<hi>Samſon;</hi> ſhew mercie in iuſtice to thoſe, that are appointed to dye. It is enough that their bodies doe dye for the ſinnes of their ſoules: bee not cruell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them: neither ſuffer your executioners to play the parts of tormentors, delighting themſelues to adde ſorrow to the ſorrowfull; mouing a ſtout ſpirit to caſt away their ſoules together with their
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3077:35"/>bodies. Be pleaſed to know, as no Ancient faith: that,<note place="margin">Ambroſ. ad Var. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Luc. lib. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Manſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>tus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo cordis eſt medi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us.</hi> And againe, <hi>Beatus qui ſoueritat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; man ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, vt alt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> diſe ipl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>d ſeruetur, al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>nt
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primatur.</hi> But here (right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) I weepe with the Prophet, 2. King. 8.12.13. to remember, what ſome in places of office haue down: and to thinke, what ſome
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> would doe, if the Lord reſtrained them not: how in colour of office and pretence of law, iuſtice is wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ied, and the Lords people abuſed; which maketh me to thinke, that if they had Prince, and Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>, and law, and all, to backe them, no ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging crueltie would be left vndone. Well, God Almightie bleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vs, and keepe vs in his holy feare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> make vs vpright-harted, and conſtant in the profeſſion of religion; and meeke and milde bearted to ſuch as are ſubiect to our cenſures; that all may ſee, we ſeeke the Lord, and not our ſelues; the conuerſion of others, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3077:35"/>not the ſatisfying of on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> owne paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, as the Lord crieth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Ieruſalem, ſo let vs learne,<note place="margin">Ier. 9.1.2. Matth. 23.37. Luk. 19.42.</note> when we ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the froward and wicked diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the world, that will not be reclaimed by any warning, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mercie of God: let vs (I ſay) do, as God, and Chriſt hath
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>: let vs
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and weepe for the ſinnes of the land. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was
<hi>Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ds</hi> compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 119.53.136.</note> whoſe eyes guſhed forth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, becauſe men kept not the Law. It is ſaid, that ſharpe vineger will ſoften the ſtonie Alpes: but briniſh teares of the Magiſtrate, wil mollifie the hardeſt heart, if (it bee not without grace) for lamenting euer the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rable, is a ſtrong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement to draw teares, if it bee b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for companie.</p>
               <p>It is the cuſtome of ſome vaine profeſſors, (for ſo I may call them) to raile odiouſly as them, that will not be ruled by their words. And ſo it is, of ſome cholericke and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe preachers, whoſe faſhion it is
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3077:36"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:3077:36"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:3077:37"/>in the pulpit to raile on them, that will not at the firſt come, and lay their hands vnder their f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et. O that they would learne of God, how to bee affected <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. And as many among you as feare God, when your peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or your children,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> your ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts, or your friends, or your neighbours, will not be gouerned, raile not; but weepe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and lament; for the hardneſſe of their hearts: i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may be the Lord will giue them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance:<note place="margin">Luk. 19.42.</note> ſo did Chriſt. For hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart is a ſickneſſe ſent of God, and lieth not in the power of man to cure. Therefore caſt not off thy people, nor children, nor thy ſeruants, nor thy neighbours, when they bee ſicke; but viſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them; and pray for them. But if they deſpiſe and neglect the ſorrowes, cares, and (as it were) the teares, which Gods Angels, and men doe make for their rebellion; then they are deſperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinfull; and vnto ſuch ſwine caſt not your pearles.</p>
               <p>Now a word of the affection, as
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3077:37"/>it is from the Prophet, <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. This piti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll mournfull, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der affection in the Prophet cach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that the Miniſters of Chriſt ought to beare a under affection, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to haue a compaſſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the member<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Church,<note place="margin">Exod. 32.32. Rom. 9.3.</note> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oued here. Becauſe the Miniſters are, or ſhould bee, their ſpirituall fathers, to beget them by the word of the Goſpell,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.2. &amp; 3.4. 1. Cor. 4.4.15.</note> or a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iſh them by the word of truth. For the tenders affection, loue, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the Paſtor toward the people, and the people toward their Paſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> is
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſingular meanes of enlarging Chriſts kingdome, and to encreaſe the Church of God in earth; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it greatly gaineth a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>otion and was Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> wiſedome: Is was Chriſts care to leaue it:<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1. Ioh. 13.14. Ioh.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.34.</note> as a charge, before he aſcended. 1. Iob, 3.11.14.18.23. &amp; 4.16. When the people perceiue the doctrines and reprehenſions to proceed from loue, then doe they delight to heare the word of God from their
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3077:38"/>mouthes; then doe their affections enlighten their vnderſtandings, and their vnderſtanding encline their wils to obedience. So long as this affection was betweene <hi>Paul,</hi> and the people in Galaria;<note place="margin">Galat. 4.14.</note> ſo long the Church encreaſed, it flouriſhed, their faith was glorious, their reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion famous, their liues godly; and if they had ſo continued, their ends had been happie.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> The vſe may ſerue to teach vs, that nothing more hindreth: the growth of the Goſpell, then the ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enation of affection, betweene Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and people. This our learned aduerſaries the Papiſh know, and therefore glory of their religion to be onely true; becauſe of the vnity and loue that is betweene Prieſts, and Papiſts; and haue wherewith to crie out of vs; that Proteſtance bee not onely againſt Papiſts, but Proteſtants againſt Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, as you deſire the enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſts kingdome, to haue your faith glorious, your Church
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3077:38"/>famous, your
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oes godly, and your ends happie; labour to nouriſh v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and loue, in affection, betweene Paſtor &amp; people, and liue together to futhers and children: otherwiſe hereſies will diſquiet you, diuiſions moleſt you, ignorance will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ne you, and the wrath of God will conſume you.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> And bee it ſerue to reproue ſuch in the , micriſterie, who in a proud manner, doe diſdaine to vſe kindly the ſheepe of Chriſt, as being ſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from that they ſhould be.<note place="margin">Cant. 5.7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ich bee ſaid for the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in the Acclamation.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> I paſſe to the ſecond branch, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the voice, in which God calleth vnto them, <hi>O Ieruſalem, waſb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God ſpeaketh to Ieruſalem, (bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Prince of the Prouinces) not in a beſeeching, but in a comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding voice; not obſecratiue, but imperatiue.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> Forcing vpon the conſciences of the hearets, that God will not
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3077:39"/>haue his Church the leſſe to eſtem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of his word, becauſe men, like ous ſelues ſpeake it; nor that we ſhould thinke it an indifferent thing, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we obey it or no, for that men like our ſelues pronounce it: but it is Gods will, that his people doe eſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e of the authority of his. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, as of Gods owne authority; regar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ling their ſermons and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements,<note place="margin">2 Chr.
29.25. 1. Sam. 15.24.</note> as God, owne word.</p>
               <p>For it is the dutie of the Church to be pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſwaded, when ſhe he truth the Miniſter preach according to Gods word, that ſhe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rrth God himſelfe ſpeake vnto her. To this purpoſe ſaith our Prophet, in the perſon of the Lord;<note place="margin">Ierem. 29.20.</note>
                  <hi>Heare yee the word of the Lord, all ye of the capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity.</hi> And this doth the Apoſtle giue for doctrine, 1. Theſ.
4.2. <hi>Yee know what commandements wee guae you by the Lord Ieſus:</hi> and therefore in the 8 verſ. he ſaith: He that deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth their ſermons, doth not deſpiſe man, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> but God: and to the ſame effect Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, 2. Pet.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3077:39"/>1.21. <hi>The prophr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> came not in old time by the will of man; but holy men of God ſpake as they were moued</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>by the ſpirit of God:</hi> therefore our Sauiour ſaith, Luk. 10.16. <hi>He that heareth you, heareth me, &amp;c.</hi> The reaſon is, becauſe by them the power of God ought to bee made knowne, whoſe ſeruant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they are.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> The vſe ſerueth to confirme our iudgements, that the Church and people of God, neuer profit by hearing of Gods word, till they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme and beleeue the words of the Lords Prophets, to bee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords owne words; and their Sermons to be the very Sermons of God. For doubtfulneſſe and incredulity, is a hainous ſinne, the cauſe of other ſinnes. Againſt this, Chriſt much laboured, Ioh. 1.18. ſhewing the Iewes that they might beleeue, that he onely declared God vnto them. Ioh.
8.28.40. and that he ſpoke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but that, which he was taught of the Father. Ioh. 15.15. And if our
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3077:40"/>Sauiour had not bold this point, a point of importance, hee would not thus haue enforced this hiſtoricall faith vpon their conſciences. Oh my beloued, know it for certaine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that the want of giuing, credit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Gods word, is no little cauſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the ſinnes wee commit. For could people liue as they doe, if they beleeued our preaching? wee may well therefore ſay with the Prophet, <hi>To whom is the arms of the Lord reuealed?</hi> Fearefull is it to ſee ſome men to make no more of the Sermons of the Lords Prophets, and ſeruants, then of a fullers ſong. Ezech. 33.31.32. <hi>Then art vnto them as a ieſting ſong, of one that hath a pleaſant voice, and can ſing well: for they hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thy words, but they doe them not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond vſe, is to confirme our iudgements, touching the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and largeneſſe of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the Lords Miniſters; that it is not light, ſmall, &amp; of no worth, but very great and waighty. And
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3077:40"/>this is worthie (in theſe our euill daies) the inforcing. For Miniſters preachings (with too many) is not ſo much reſpected, as a winters tale, nor the Church of ſo much e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme, as an Ale-houſe. But I hope better things of you, that you will not lightly regard their authority, of whom Chriſt hath witneſſed. Mat. 16.18.
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> againſt which the gates of hell ſhal not preuaile. And for their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, it is very large, Ier. 11.10. <hi>Behold, I haue ſet you ouer nations, and king domes, to plucke vp, and to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> out, to deſtroy, and to throw downs, to build, and to plant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore beleeue it,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God haue authority to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue Kings and Princes,<note place="margin">Iere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 27.2.</note> (as the Prophet ſaith:) but not to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate Kings, as the Papiſts ſay.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> They haue authority to counſell &amp; exhort Kings, as God hath ſaid; but: not to dethrone, depoſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and kill Kings; as the Prieſts, and blood-thirſty Ieſuites ſay.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:3077:41"/>
               <p>The Miniſter hath authority,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſts name to pronounce
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinnes to all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, (as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith; 20.150) but not to curſe &amp; abſolue whom he will, (as the Pope ſaith.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Hee hath authority to reproue things amiſſe, in Church, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, by doctrine, (as the word ſaith) but not of himſelfe to reforme by practiſe, as Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, and Browniſts ſay.</p>
               <p>So that eſtabliſhing, or remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of Princes belongs to God onely; and forgiueneſſe of ſinnes to God onely; and the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bernation of Church and Common-wealth, belongs to Princes onely: built he reprouing of ſins in all, belongeth to Miniſters alſo.</p>
               <p>And this is the Innocency of the Doue, and the wiſdome of the Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, that ought to bee done in loue, in order, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in place, with diſcretion and circum ſpectious:
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſoule for ſoule, if wee doe no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:3077:41"/>
               <p>Here I become in the Lords be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe an humble ſutor vnto you, that as the Lord hath honoured your Honour with authority; ſo you would bring all your honour and authority, to honour Ieſus Chriſt in his Miniſters. They are but ſeruants, bee not angry with them; they muſt deliuer their Lords meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, it is nothing to them; agree with their Lord and Maſter, and they will be content.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Laſtly, this doctrine crieth vpon vs, to haue reuerent eſtimation and regard of the Miniſterie, and not contemne the Prophets, leſt wee grow to deſpiſe prophecie.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. Becauſe God ſpeaketh by them, they preſent the perſon and voice of the Lord vnto vs; and ſhould not wee reuerence them? they are the Lords Embaſſadors, and may not they ſtand couered before vs? they are the Angels of the Lord of Hoſts, at whoſe feet,
<hi>Iohn</hi> the Apoſtle ſell downe; and ſhould wee ſpurne them with our
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:3077:42"/>feet? They are the Fathers, and Stewards of our Countrey, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the foode of our ſoules; and ſhould wee denie them the food of their bodies? They are the ſtrength of the land, euen the Chariots and Horſemen of England; and ſhould wee not defend them? But heere I ſtand amazed, deſiring teares, rather then words, to lament the contempt of the Lords ſeruants. Time was, when their feet were beautifull, that brought the glad tidings of the Goſpell: but <hi>O quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum mutatus ab illo.</hi> Now their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are reiected. Time was, yea time is, that the face of a ſmoakie <hi>Kemarius,</hi> a ſillie Frier, hath been, and is, more regarded, then the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a Reucrend Biſhop: yet
<hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> called them Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, that ſpeaking with a Biſhop, or of a Biſhop, and would not call him Biſhop, not Archbiſhop, not moſt religions, nor moſt holy: yea graue Paſtors, and poinfull Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, are (with ſome) not ſo much
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:3077:42"/>reſpected, as al the make-bates, and tale-bearers of the world. <hi>O tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, ô mores!</hi> Is our God of leſſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, our religion of leſſe worth, our ſoules of leſſe account with vs, then with them? farte be it from vs. Once an Ancient ſaid;
<hi>Tutior est diſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tis, quàm docentis conditio:</hi> It is better to learne, then to teach. But we may ſay: <hi>Tutior eſt peccan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, quàm argaintis conditio:</hi> It is more ſafer to commit ſinne, then to reproue frone. For to tell any of their vncloanneſſe, is to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a prey. For doe wee not liue to ſee the Preachers mocked, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> was; the Sabboths polluted, and the Princeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of all profeſſions, (I meane Diuinity) the preaching of the word become vile in reſpect, the pooreſt in practiſe, and the meaneſt in ſhew? What ſhall I ſay vnto you, or how ſhall I confuit you, ye ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of the Lord? are wee not diſdained? are wee not made a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing ſtocke, a table-talke, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted as the filth of the ſtreet,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:3077:43"/>and of ſcouring of all things, vnto this day: and like ſtill to continue, to exerciſe your patience, and to make triall of your humility. Yet this I am bold to ſpeake (for your comfort) that he or ſhee that deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth you, deſpiſeth the Lord Ieſus. Matth.
10.40. Luk. 10.16. Exod. 16.8. 1. Sam. 8.7.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>The third part.</head>
               <p>Now I entreate your patience to ſpeake of the matter it ſelfe: <hi>O Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, waſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sanctification is exerciſed about ſinne, and holineſſe: for wee muſt waſh, and cleanſe away ſinne and wickeducſſe; and embrace true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and righteouſneſſe: which is partly a deteſtation of former ſins, in which wee haue taken plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and partly a delight, and a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie loue of righteouſnes, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the royall law.</p>
               <p>Looking vpon the monſtrous &amp; horrid vncleanneſſe of this age, I
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:3077:43"/>ſtand amazed; whether I ſhould behold it with the eyes of <hi>Timo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> to hate it; or of <hi>Heraclîtus,</hi> to la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment for it; and whether I ſhould more hate, or lament the ſinnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time; after a ſhort pauſe, I reſolue to entreat you to ioyne your teares, with heartie prayers, to waſh away the ingrained dye of ſinne.</p>
               <p>And comming to the points, pointed for inſtruction: I beſeech you obſerue with me, that vertue is a taske, a worke, a thing, and not worden. Wofull it is to ſee, how we turne, not onely it, but the word of God into words; holding religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſanctification, but a table<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcourſe, to touch the eare, not to pierce the heart; and hold our ſelues buſied in cold controuerſies, which (in the vnlearned) rather extinguiſh then kindle zeale. But know (Right Honorable) that ſanctification and repentance is (an action) preſſed vpon vs, and that from God. For it is his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, we muſt waſh, therefore we are vncleance.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:3077:44"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> From whence the inſtruction is, that there is not any thing in al this world, that doth defile the ſoule and body in the ſight of God, as ſin doth. Proued here: That which is not defiled, need not to be waſhed. But here man is comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to waſh himſelfe: therefore he is defiled.</p>
               <p>Sinne is called rottenneſſe and corruption: and is that which wee haue drawne, either by propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from our parents in originall ſinne, which hath defiled and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted the whole nature of man, that he is blinded in vnderſtanding: froward in will, and rebelling in all his actions, againſt the will &amp; word of God: or elſe it is the increaſe of this vncleanneſſe, which wee haue greatly augmented by our owne euill practiſe, and wicked conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation: and is that which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle calleth old leauen to be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.7</note> that it may be a new lumpe. This vncleanneſſe of ſinne was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured in the ancient waſhings of <hi>Aaron,</hi> and his ſonnes with water
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:3077:44"/>at the doore of the Tabernacle, Exodus 29.4. And in the typicall and ſignifying waſhings of the old Teſtament, foreſhewing the clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and purifying of our hearts in the Goſpell.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.8.</note> For Gods Altar and ſeruice muſt bee compaſſed with innocencie: the Lord will be ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified in thoſe that come neere him.<note place="margin">Leu. 10</note> The purification of the ſoule and bodie, is the fruite of ſauing hope, 1. Ioh. 3.3. For euery one that hath this hope in him, purgeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as he is pure.</p>
               <p>This vncleannes is deciphered in Ezek. 16.6. for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, vnto whoſe eyes all things are naked,<note place="margin">Heb. 13 4.</note> ſeeth eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one polluted in his own blood.<note place="margin">Luk. 10.30.</note> It is the ſpirituall pitch, that who ſo toucheth, is defiled therewith. Sin doth mortifie vs, and maketh vs dead to grace and goodneſſe. And in the old Teſtament, he<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched a dead cark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe, was vncleane, and might not come into the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie, till he was cleanſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> The firſt vſe is, to teach vs to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:3077:45"/>with our owne hearts to hate and abhorre ſinne in all; but ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in our ſelues, and that with a perfect hatred, euen more then the diuell of hell:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> for he cannot hurt vs,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> till ſinne doe ſtaine vs. Sinne is that which much delighted the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell: and therefore it is the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters office, and continual endeuour to prouoke vs to ſinne. Therefore he is called an Enemie, Apocal.
12.10. an Accuſer, a Compaſſer, Iob. 1.7. a Siſter, Luk. 22.31. a Deceiuer, Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 3.13. Wherfore (I beſeech you) truſt him not, for hee hath a minde to get all the members of thy body, and all the affections of thy ſoule from out of Gods ſeruice, into his ſlauerie and ſubiection.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Sinne greatly diſpleaſeth God; and therefore he hath, euery where in his word, threatned fearefull pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments againſt the tranſgreſſors of his law, Leuit. 26.15. Deu. 28.15. And there hath been none ſo deare, nor is any ſo beloued vnto God, in heauen, Paradiſe, nor in the earth:
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:3077:45"/>but for ſin the Lord hath puniſhed. The Angels that kept not their firſt eſtate,<note place="margin">Iude epiſt.</note> they are reſerued in chaines of darkneſſe for euer to be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Adam</hi> for ſinne throwne out of Paradiſe. The Canaanites, with their ſixe bordering nations, diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herited, and caſt forth of their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. The firſt world drowned: So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Gomer burned: Kings vnthroaned: Iudges &amp; Magiſtrates ſtrooke downe from the bench, and the Mightie caſt from their ſeates. Yea the Lord forſooke his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, euen mount Sion which hee loued, becauſe they ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him: that ſo the ſaying of his Prophet might be true. Pſalme
5.4. <hi>Thou art not a God that loueth wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe: neither ſhall euell dwell with thee. The fooliſh ſhall not ſtand in thy ſight, for thou hateſt all them that worke iniquitie.</hi> Iſai. 1.16. <hi>Waſh you, make you cleane, put away the euill of your workes: ceaſe to doe euill, learne to doe well: and then come and let vs reaſon together.</hi> For wee muſt waſh
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:3077:46"/>our hands in innocencie, before we may come to compaſſe the Lords Altar.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Here alſo it ſerueth, to informe our iudgements concerning ſin and wickedneſſe, (namely) that euerie ſinne defileth and ſubuerteth the worke of God: it turneth good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euill; faire into ſoule; forme in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to deformitie, and life into do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. And this doth the holy Ghoſt teach vs, Tit. 1.15. ſaying: <hi>Vnto the clean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> are all things cleane: but vnto them that are defiled, and vnbeleeuing. Is nothing cleane, but euen their minds and conſciences are defiled.</hi> Should not this (deare Chriſtians) inforce vpon our conſciences this doctrine of ſanctification, and cleanſing of our fleſh and ſpirits from wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; ſuh it defileth all things it commeth neere? Let Gods word come to a ſinful he are, it is defiled, as pure water in a foule veſſell. What is there in man, or without man, that ſinne hath not defiled? It hath made our tongues become Adders
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:3077:46"/>ſpeares: our lippes, inſtruments of guile: our hands to worke iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; and our feete to runne to euill, and to ſhed blood. But what ſpeake I of the defilement of the members? the Spirit ſaith, ſin defileth the very minds and conſciences of men. And how ſhould it bee otherwiſe? for if ſin ſo abuſe the naturall parts, what will it doe with the minde? It grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth me to tell you: but I will tell you, that it may warne you. It tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth prayers into curſing: it vſeth knowledge to beguile: the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to couer prophaneneſſe: it v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. their wittes to cauill, which brings Lawyers much gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: it vſeth wealth to oppreſſe: ſtrength to ſteale, to wine and to women. It vſeth naturall wiſedome to maintaine vnnatural blaſphemy: It vſeth hunger to gluttonie: thirſt to drunk
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ues: garments to pride: honour to diſdome: marriage to luſt: offices to briberie: the Minſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie to contention: ſaw to delay. It vſeth the day to open euill, and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:3077:47"/>the night to ſecret ſhame. Shall I ceaſe here? I weepe to ſpeake it: It either deſpiſeth, or wreſteth dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably the holy and ſacred word of God, and the ordinances of God it prophaneth wickedly. For haue we not in this our age, to fill vp the meaſure of vncleanneſſe? haue we not Ribaldrie, as in Playes and the like, committed to the preſſe, to be commended in print; leſt poſteritie ſhould want patternes of impietie? Whoredome with ſome is good phyſicke; honeſtie is but foolerie; knauerie is commoditie; diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling is diſcretion, and idleneſſe is gentrie. If this bee not cleanſed with the winde of the law; or cut downe by your ſword of iuſtice, or purged with the Lords fanne; to what height of ſinne ſhall we grow vnto? But the thing which I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, is this: that God Almightie for all this, doth ſuffer vs ſtil to liue. It may be hee doth it, that his long patience might leade vs to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; or, that wee ſhould fulfill the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:3077:47"/>meaſure of ſin, in defying the grace of God, as wee haue defiled the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man: that ſo at laſt we may abuſe death, as we haue abuſed life: for ſildome doth hee dye well, that liueth euill.</p>
               <p>O, my ſoule, come not in to their habitation: woe be vnto them, for they follow the way of <hi>Caine;</hi> &amp; are caſt away with the deceit of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lams</hi> wages.</p>
               <p>And now I turne vnto you, the ſeruants of the Lord, that haue as great care to keepe ſinne from their ſoules, as ſickneſſe from your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: I beſeech you in the feare of God, and in the waightie conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of your own ſinnes, euen for the Lords ſake, for your poore ſoules ſake, and for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, that was made ſinne for vs;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.20.</note> hearken to the counſell of our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, crying aloud in the audience of you all: O Ieruſalem, waſh thy heart from wickedneſſe, deteſt and abhorre thy former ſinnes, forſake thy old way, walke in newneſſe of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:3077:48"/>life, caſt away the workes of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and put on the Armour of light.<note place="margin">Rom. 13.12. Prou. 24.16.</note> Hate all ſin paſt, care to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent ſinne to come, and entertaine it not, offering it ſelfe againe. For the iuſt falleth, and riſeth againe: but the wicked fall into miſchiefe. And this endeauouring, the bleſſed ſpirit will helpe our infirmities, and our heauenly Father make vs white in the blood of the Lambe, Apoc. 7.14. For this is not the worke of fleſh and blood, although man bee ſpoken vnto (as though he had po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to doe it) but it is the action and worke of the whole Trinitie; and yet it is commanded, as it were our worke;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.10.</note> becauſe God worketh in vs, not as in ſtockes and ſtones, but as in reaſonable creatures: for wee, (by the worke of his grace) worke together with him, yet ſtill ſo, as that ſanctification is ſtill wholly from God.</p>
               <p>For firſt,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.23.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t. 3.5. Epheſ.
2.26.</note> God the Father ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, by giuing his Sonne; God the Sonne ſanctifieth, by mortifying
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:3077:48"/>our ſinnes by his blood; and the holy Ghoſt ſanctifieth, by applying the vertue of Chriſts death and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection vnto vs.<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.5</note> And we may be ſaid to ſanctifie our ſelues, when we applie our will, deſire and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, in the vſe of the meanes or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God. And thus much bee ſaid for the generall.</p>
               <p>Now let vs in Gods feare, fall vpon the particulars. And firſt, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification is an action, teaching vs, that true religion, and vndefiled, conſiſteth not in a ſpeculatiue, or contemplatiue profeſſion, but in an actiue, and practiue conuerſation in holineſſe: for knowledge without obedience, encreaſeth puniſhment, Luk. 12, 47.<note place="margin">Mat. 7.22 24. Luk. 11.28. Iam. 1.23 25.27.</note> For <hi>not euery one that ſaith Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the kingdome, but he that doth the will of the Father.</hi> For pure religion, and vndefiled before God the Father, is this, to viſit the fatherleſſe and wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, in their aduerſitie. <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Martha</hi> will doe well, ſo they be both in one houſe: ſo will Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:3077:49"/>profeſſion and practiſe, if they meet both in one ſoule. Let a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian take it a ſhame to bee like an Athenian, (that is) to know what appertaineth vnto vertue, but not to practiſe it. And the God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen make vs all, not only knowers, ſpeakers, Preachers, and profeſſors of Gods word, but doers thereof, that we may be ſaued.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> Againe, as it is a worke, ſo it is a worke, that may not be performed by an Atturney; but by our ſelues in our owne perſons: for our ſelues muſt doe it; for the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is,
<hi>Waſh thy, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From whence the doctrine is, that God requireth of euery Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, that hee performe the parts of Gods worſhip, and the duties of charity, actually himſelfe vnto God and men, before hee depart hence, for himſelfe, and not by others for him.</p>
               <p>Our learned aduerſaries beare the world in hand, that as we come to earthly Princes, by mediators,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:3077:49"/>and ſolicitors; ſo Chriſtians ought to come to the Prince of Princes. For they hold it preſumption to preaſe into the preſence of the King of heauen, without the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of many.</p>
               <p>If our God did feare the treaſons of any, or did not know, or remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the wants of all his children himſelfe; or if hee could not heare all the ſutes of all the world at one inſtant; and if hee had not appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his onely Sonne, to be the onely meanes, in whom wee haue promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed acceſſe: then their perſwaſion might haue paſſed for doctrine.</p>
               <p>But the contrary on Gods part to vs is true.</p>
               <p>Therefore let vs know, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens good workes ſhall do no good for vs; nor others prayers for vs, without our owne workes, and prayers for our ſelues. For nothing more (beloued brethren) hath ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Church and Common-wealth, then doing duties, <hi>non per ſe, ſed per alium.</hi> It hath brought ignorance
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:3077:50"/>into the Church, and briberie into the Common-wealth; which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued our renouned Soueralgue, King <hi>Iames,</hi> in his <hi>Baſili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on Doro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, l.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="35">35. to giue this charge to the Prince his Sonne, that be ſpare not any paines in his owne perſon, to ſee iuſtice executed; giuing for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, his moſt worthie Grand-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of famous memory, whoſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour was to bee ſtiled, and called, the poore mans King: And in the 55. page, his Maieſty counſelleth the Prince, once a yeere to viſit the principall parts of the kingdome, not referring to Vice-royes; but to heare the complaints himſelfe, and to decide the principall matter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, in his owne perſon.</p>
               <p>And here you ſee the exerciſes of religion, and parts of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, muſt bee done actually, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally of euery one of the Lords ſeruants, for themſelues.</p>
               <p>This you call for at our hands, the Preacher muſt be reſident, (ſay you) and muſt preach for himſelfe;
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:3077:50"/>and muſt not the hearer heare for himſelfe alſo? why ſay you one to another, go you to day to Church, and ſerue God for me; and I will ſerue God for you to morrow. This conceit moueth certaine to prepare Bead-men to pray, while they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues play. But learne of our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, the parts of Gods worſhip muſt be performed of euery one of vs for our ſelues: for anothers faith can not ſaue vs; wee muſt pray for our ſelues; for our requeſts are g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eed according to our owne faith, <hi>Be is vnto thee, as thou be le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt.</hi> Therefore repent for thy ſelft, confeſſe thine owne ſinne, rather then another ſhall declare it: doe good workes for thy ſelfe; for to giue blackes, and large almes is good; but one pennie with thine owne hand, is a precious ſacrifice in the eyes of God. Remember the ſaying. Gala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 6.10. <hi>While we haue time
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e vs</hi> (we our ſelues) <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> good vnto all men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. The reaſon i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, becauſe the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:3077:51"/>Prophet giueth it for doctrine, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bac. 2.4.
<hi>For the iuſt ſhall liue by his owne faith:</hi> marke the word (his)<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Becauſe wee may as well ſee by another mans eyes, as goe to heauen by another mans workes.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Becauſe the queſtion in the day of daies ſhall not be, what other men haue done for vs? but what wee haue done for our ſelues, Mat. 35.42. that is, whether with our owne hands wee haue giuen meate to the hungry, drinke to the thirſty, harbour to the ſtranger, clothes to the naked; and whether in our own perſons wee haue viſited the ſicke, and in priſon: for the duties of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty bee not onely actuall, but perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall duties, and required of euery Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Now to make ſome vſe of this which hath been ſpoken; It may firſt enforme the vnderſtanding, that the good works, which others doe for vs, doe vs no good vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. They doe good to others for preſeruation.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:3077:51"/>
               <p>And this doth confute the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perirrogate workes of the Papiſts, who make vs beleeue, though our owne lamps bee without oyle, wee may borrow plentifully of the Saints: For the Saints (ſay they) haue not onely kept all Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, but haue done more then God hath commanded, and ſo the ſurpluſſage of their good workes, hang vp vpon the Popes tallie, for ſuch as want, and will pay moſt for them. But this vntruth ſo long hanged vpon the pin of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh traditions, Chriſt Ieſus cutteth downe, Luk. 17.10. When you haue done all that is commanded you, ſay, that you are vnprofitable ſeruants.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Further, it ſerueth to teach vs,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 95.7.</note> that in this life onely, by the grace of God in Chriſt, we procute mercy and ſaluation at the hands of God.<note place="margin">Heb. 37 &amp; 4.7. 1. Cor. 6.2.</note> So that in this life onely, heauen is to bee obtained, or loſt for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more: after this life there is no time to worke. Here we winne and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:3077:52"/>loſe life eternall. <hi>Cyprian. in ſer. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mortal. circ. med. Hortamur d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> facult as adeſt, dum ad huc aliquid de ſaculo ſupereſt,</hi> wee exhort you to ſerue God while you may; while wee are in the world, let vs come from the depth of darke ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to the bright light of true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. For,
<hi>Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um iſtinc exceſſum fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crit, nullus
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> locus poenit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntiae, nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus ſatisfactionis effectus.</hi> For after this life, there is no place of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, nor any ſatisfaction.
<hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braſe</hi> is one with this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <hi>Qui
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> his non accipit remiſſionem pecc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m, &amp;c.</hi> He that receiueth not remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinnes heere, ſhall not come there, that is, in heauen. Not onely friends, but our aduerſaries are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidene with vs in this truth. <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> their Angelicall Doctor.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.9.13. <hi>ar.</hi> 4.
<hi>ad.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 9.62.
<hi>ar.</hi> 9. <hi>corpor.</hi> ſaith: <hi>Dicendum, quod me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reri &amp; d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>merer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> ad ſlas
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Wee muſt ſay, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>to merit, or demerit, pertaine to the ſtate of the way, that is, to this life. And thus
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:3077:52"/>the learned Papiſt hath lent vs his hand to butie Purgatorie for euer. For if heere wee obtaine, what doe ſoules there? And ſo much bee ſaid for the matter, what muſt be done.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="circumstance">
               <head>The fourth Circumſtance.</head>
               <p>I now paſſe to the fourth Branch, expreſſing the Subiect that muſt be waſhed, which is, the heart. For, <hi>O Ieruſalem, waſh thy heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt Ieſus waſhed others,<note place="margin">Iohn,
13.5.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee himſelſe was the Lambe without ſlaine. But Ieruſalem, that waſhed others in the poole of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh.
5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> muſt waſh her ſelfe.</p>
               <p>It is the deſire of corrupt fleſh and blood, to fiſh in other mens wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But the well taught Chriſtian will content himſelfe with the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his owne well.</p>
               <p>If wee would open an vnpartiall eye, when we be at home<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as we do when we goe abroad; we ſhould ſee more be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes in our owne eye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in our neighbou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:3077:53"/>more ſtaines and ſins in our owne liues, then in others. But wee that are quicke ſighted in other mens faults, and blind in our owne, bee here taken to taske, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, firſt to finde out our owne fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe, and waſh away our owne wickedneſſe, before wee meddle with others. <hi>O Ieruſalem, waſh thy heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> From whence (I pray you learn) that the Lords will is, that ſuch that are in high places, and are to deale with the ſinnes of others, ought firſt to cleanſe themſelues, and waſh their owne hearts; informe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme themſelues, before they goe about to reforme others. When <hi>Abſalon</hi> would deceiue his fathers people,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.3.</note> hee ſaid, euery mans cauſe was good: ſo Satan to deceiue the world, maketh euery man thinke another man to bee euill, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to bee good. But the holy Ghoſt chargeth euery one, not to be too fauourable to himſelfe, but to ſuruey our owne manners, our
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:3077:53"/>owne wits, our own ſenſes, our own members, our own hearts muſt firſt bee ſet vpon, and wee muſt cleanſe our owne conſciences from dead workes: wee muſt waſh our owne moates, and pull out our owne beames, Matth. 7.3. <hi>Ieremy</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maudeth, to ſearch our waies,<note place="margin">Lamen. 3.40.</note> and to examine our own liues, to iudge our owne ſinnes; keepe Seſſions at home firſt, before wee goe abroad, and cleanſe firſt our owne houſes, our owne Citie, our owne ſtreetes. For loue and good workes ſhould begin at home.</p>
               <p>For how can a maſter reproue a ſeruant, for lying, and deceiuing, and make a trade of it himſelfe?</p>
               <p>With what heart can a parent correct his child for ſwearing; and ſweare continually himſelfe?</p>
               <p>How faintly wil a Miniſter preach againſt vſurie, and againſt drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and againſt pride, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe; and be ſpotted with all theſe himſelfe?</p>
               <p>What zeale may we looke for in
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:3077:54"/>ſome officers to puniſh ſwearing, and blaſphemie, and the prophana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sabbath; when they themſelues let faith and truth paſſe daily from betweene their lippes? can they with any zeale puniſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in others, when they haue ſo little conſcience of theſe ſinnes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues? O, I beſeech you, looke to theſe things, you that bee the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dars of London. For your fall is not your owne alone: but you craſh in peeces al that are vnder you. Do are brethren, take the word of the Lord to heart, ſaying: O man who ſoeuer thou art that iudgeſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.1.2.3.4.</note> thou condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt thy ſelfe: for thou that iudgeſt another, doſt the ſame things thou that ſaieſt a man ſhould not ſteale, not lie, nor ſweare, not deceiue, not drinke to bee drunken; doeſt thou ſteale, doeſt thou lie? &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The God of heauen and earth giue vs power to iudge our ſelues, euen in the ſame things wee iudge and puniſh others; and to cleanſe our ſelues of the ſins we condemne
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:3077:54"/>in others. And euer giue vs grace, O Lord, firſt to ſit iudge in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> court of our owne conſcience,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.28.</note> before we ſit as iudge in the ſoule of our neighbour.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> The firſt vſe entreateth vs to learne this dutie, to bee ſtricter to our ſelues then to any other. It hath been an old ſaying, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nne quiſque proximus ſibi:</hi> for hee that loueth not himſelf, wil not loue any: <hi>Potés<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne alium malius noſcere quàm to ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum:</hi> Canſt thou know another bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then thy ſelfe? It being ſo, let me become a ſuter, for your owne gaine: be ſtraighter in all things to your ſelues then to others: and be more liberall in ſome things to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, then to your ſelues: merkely be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t with that, in another, which you will not doe in your ſelfe.</p>
               <p>A worthy obſeruation: For many Magiſtrates &amp; maſters take libertie to do y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, which if their ſeruants doe, they muſt ſharply be rebuked, if not puniſhed; as though <hi>peco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tum,</hi> were only ſinne in the inferiour: No, no,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:3077:55"/>whatſoeuer is ſinne in any one, <hi>in omnibus eſt peccatum:</hi> otherwiſe it worketh ſtraightneſſe to others, &amp; libertie to our ſelues. As it is in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that profeſſe irregularitie, and thinke it lawfull, themſelues to doe any thing; and yet cenſure and find fault with other mens vertues, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues flowing full of all vice. Theſe be ſuch, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they get between the pot and the wall, deſpiſe go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, and ſpeake euill of thoſe that bee in authoritie. Some you ſhall ſee, who being vnwilling to vſe a Ceremonie themſelues, iudge ſtraightly all others (as hainous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders) that vſe it: and other, that vſe it themſelues, yet find fault with ſuch, that doe but ſo.</p>
               <p>But touching theſe things indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent,<note place="margin">Ro.
14.3.14. &amp; 15.12. 1. Cor. 8.8 and 9.10. &amp; 10.23.</note> I pray you learne not to iudge that in others, which you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe your ſelues: for albeit our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion be but one, yet our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, through the ignorance that is in them, may be diuers. This being practiſed of vs, will moue vs to caſt
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:3077:55"/>the firſt ſtone at our ſelues.<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.7.</note> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how that the Lord Ieſus was angry with S. <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 21.22.</note> for being a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie-bodie in <hi>Iohns</hi> matters. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore plow vp your own fallow, and ſow your owne ground: waſh your owne hearts, pull firſt the beames out of your own cies, leaſt the Lord reproue thee, as he did Saint
<hi>Peter,</hi> with what is that to thee?</p>
               <p>Laſtly, this doctrine ſpeaketh to you (my Lord) and to your brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the Magiſtrates of this honourable Citie; whom God hath made as an eye to ſee, as the mouth to reproue, and as the hands to correct ſinne. The Lord aboue requireth at your hands, that eſpecially you looke to your ſelues, that you ſin not, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in ſuch ſinnes you cenſure in others; and that you beare with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in that wherein you are temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted your ſelues. For the ſinnes of the heads indanger all the members. For what is more abſurd, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if they (I ſay) that ſhould cleanſe and waſh Ieruſalem, the Citie, the Church,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:3077:56"/>and Common-wealth of blemiſhes and wickedneſſe, ſhould happen to be full of ſpots themſelues. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the eye no other member can doe his office: neither hand nor foote can doe his function without ſight. It hath been ſaid of old, that the religion and ſanctitie of the people, is in the religion of the Prince. Wherefore reuerend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and Iudges of others, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pray you, for your owne ſakes, for the Churches ſake, for the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths ſake, &amp; for the Lords ſake, take knowledge of your owne hearts: and know, that when you haue moates in your eyes, they breed beames in others. And I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you look to it, that they grow not to be beames. For you fall not alone, but your currant is as the maine Ocean, that drowneth other in perdition.</p>
               <p>But I haſte to the ſubſtance.</p>
               <p>The Prophet doth not here co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Ieruſalem to waſh her feete only, with the Diſciples: nor her
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:3077:56"/>hands with the double minded: nor her head only with 8. <hi>Peter,</hi> but her hears<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not the outſide only, but the inſide alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> From whence the holy Ghoſt commendeth this doctrine: That outward holineſſe, without the heart goe with it, is an abomination before God. All religion, as is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for faſhion,<note place="margin">Ioh. 11.</note> is like <hi>Mary</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<hi>Martha,</hi> &amp; like <hi>Lazarus</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt. For comming vnto the Sanctuary of the Lord; praying and receiuing of Sacraments; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Sermons, fetching many a fained ſigh, and ſpeaking many an ignorant Amen; the thinking that the ſanctifying of the Sabbath li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the putting on of their beſt apparell, and ſuch like: when as in the meane while with the Iewes, Iſai. 57.8. it may be ſaid, behind the doores and poſts thou haſt ſet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrances, of deepe hypocriſie, and open idolatrie. If wee come with ſuch hearts before the Lord, the ſame reproofe is for vs, that
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:3077:57"/>
                  <hi>I ſay</hi> ſpeaketh, cap. 1.11.
<hi>What haue I to doe with the multitude of your ſacrifices, ſaith the Lord? I am full of the burnt offerings of rammes and the fat of the beaſts: and I deſire not the blood of bullocks, nor of lambes, nor of goates.</hi> For the outward ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of religion, without the cleannes and ſinceritie of the heart, is abominable vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord.<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.16</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith the Lord, <hi>Waſh you, make you cleane, &amp;c.</hi> And to this end our Sauiour giueth a caueat: Take heed of the leuen of the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,<note place="margin">Luk. 12 1.</note> which is externall worſhip. For the Lord is wearie of our knee-prayers, our lip-labours without the heart,<note place="margin">Eſay. 29 13.</note> our time-ſeruing hearers: who draw neere the Lord with their mouth, and honour him with their lippes; but their heart is farre from him, as he ſaith himſelfe. And yet not ſo farre,<note place="margin">Pro. 16.2.</note> but the Lord ſeeth well enough where they be: for he pondereth the ſpirits. Oh conſider this you that pray and preach, and giue and forgiue to be ſeene of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:3077:57"/>there be but too many that confeſſe their faults, and weepe for their ſins too, and but for ſhew onely; many come through Cathedrall Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and kneele downe by a pillar, as though they prayed, but their hearts bee not cleane, nor vpright with God.</p>
               <p>This humor waiteth vpon vs all:<note place="margin">Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 14.17. Luk. 17.20.</note> happie is hee that entertaineth it not. For it maketh all that we doe, fruitleſſe before God.</p>
               <p>Therefore (I beſeech you) in all the exerciſes of religion, let vs pray with <hi>Dauid: Not vnto vs, O Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm. 115.1.</note> 
                  <hi>not vnto vs, but to thy name giue the praiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> The vſe is, to reproue ſuch as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue themſelues with ſhewes and ſhadowes, in ſtead of ſubſtance; that take Chriſt in their mouthes, religion in their eyes, mortification in their for faſts; their holineſſe, in keeping their canonicall houres; and their deuotion only in holding vp their hands, and croſſing their fote-heads. For in this ſeruice wee
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:3077:58"/>deceiue our brethren with ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, offend our God with ſhewes, and our ſelues with ſinnes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wee depriue our heares of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, our liues of holin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, and our ſelues of ſaluation. Galath. 6.7. But God is not mocked, for whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a man ſoweth, that ſhall he alſo
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eape.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> The ſecond vſe teacheth vs, that there is no ſeruice acceptable to God, except the whole heart goe with it. As all the workes of Gods mercy to vs, vnleſſe God come with it, is vaine: ſo all our workes, and words to God, vnleſſe the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> goe with it, be likewiſe all in vain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. It is not good wordes, not holy Pſalmes, nor yet an outward good practiſe that the Lord regardeth,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.15. Match. 6.1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> except the heart goe with it. <hi>Take head</hi> (ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith Chriſt)
<hi>ye giue not your alm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> before men, to be ſeem of them.</hi> 1. Reg. 8.47. <hi>If they turne againd vnto their heart, in the land to the which they be carried away a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c.</hi> Let vs therefore (deare bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren)
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:3077:58"/>clenſe out hearts, and in our externall workes of Gods worſhip, ſend them vp, together with the worke, without hypocrifie, in the ſeruice of God. For of all ſickneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the falling euill is the worſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it maketh one ſeeme with out life. And of all euils, hypocrifie is the worſt, for is maketh one ſeeme that he is not. Some ſeeme to pray, when they curſe; ſome to pretend friendſhip, when (with <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>das</hi>) trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is in their heart: ſome pretend diſcharge of office, to pinch the poore, and kiſſe their hand: but let the ſudden ends, and fearfull deaths of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> worke ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity in our hearts, and holineſſe in our liues.</p>
               <p>But yet I haue not done with the heart.</p>
               <p>The Lord ſaith, Ier. 17.9. that the heart is deceitfull and wicked aboue all things, who can know it? That which the Lord queſtioneth, maketh any vnderſtanding to faile, and my tongue to cleaue to the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:3077:59"/>roofe of my mouth, rather then to ſhew you what is meant by the heart. Neuertheleſſe Gods word biddeth me to ſay, that the heart is taken in the language of Canaan, for the corrupted, and depraued qualities of the heart; and not for the lumpe of fleſh, and materiall heart in man, which is the good creature of God: and ſomtimes it is taken for the whole inward man, 1. Pet. 3.4. <hi>Let the hid man of the heart be vncorrupt, with a meeke and quiet ſpirit, which is before God, a thing much ſet by:</hi> And ſomtimes it is vnderſtood for the thoughts and affections corrupted, and ſo it is in this place.</p>
               <p>The heart is the firſt liuer, and the laſt dier; let the heart be clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſanctified, and thou wilt begin well, and end well; liue well, and die well.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> The doctrine is, that
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee cannot haue a ſanctified life, ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> we haue a cleane and ſanctified heart.<note place="margin">Match. 15.19.</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (ſaith our Prophet) <hi>O Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:3077:59"/>waſh thy heart.</hi> For out of the heart come euill thoughts, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, adulteries, fornicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, thefts, falſe teſtimonies, &amp; ſlanders. Make the tree good,<note place="margin">Mat.
12.33.</note> and his fruit will bee good. For the heart is as a King, &amp; fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>(capſula cordis)</hi> his throne and ſtate, with his <hi>animales vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,</hi> his attendants; vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, reaſon, memorie, will and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections about him; and all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther members of the body bow at his becke. If hee be ioyfull, all will reioyce with him; if hee feare, they all treable; if the heart bee a ſinfull and an vncleane heart, all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are vncleane.</p>
               <p>For when within bee lodged in the breaſts of Ieſuites and Ieſuited Papiſts, miſchieuous imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, foule affections, malice, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and what not? then the eyes rowle to wantonneſſe, the tongue raueth, in railing vpon Prince and people: the care bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneth to rebellion, and falſe tales, to ſet whole Cities and Countries
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:3077:60"/>on fire with contention: the hands embrew themſelues in the blood of their betters: Hence commeth the king-killing doctrine, treaſons, and maſſacres abroad in the world; and hence is it, that ſubiects ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Magiſtrates, people againſt Paſtors, children againſt their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, ſeruants againſt their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, &amp; home-bred people againſt the mother and nation that concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them, brought them forth, and nouriſhed them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist of Rome</note> And heere I dare boldly ſay of him, that would be the ſoules Lord, and the chiefeſt Biſhop of the Churches compaſſe; that his heart is not right with God, nor cleanſed from wickedneſſe, ſo long as his hands bee died in the blood of the Saints.</p>
               <p>But to returne to our ſelues; cleere your fountaines, before you ſweepe your channelles; &amp; ſearch the bottome of your wounds, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you plaiſter the ſore; cleanſe your hearts, and all ſhall bee well.
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:3077:60"/>For if the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rt be good, the tongue will vtter forth good matter,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 45.1.</note> and ſpeak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for the King; and not raile vpon Rulers, nor ſpeak euil of thoſe that are in authority.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> The ſumme of all this is, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade vs to confirme our iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, touching the cauſe of all ſinfull actions; that an vncleane and corrupt heart, is the fountaine of all ſinfull actions. For an euill heart will ſchoole vs to all manner of ſinne, and bring vs to deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, albeit wee ſhould neuer ſee p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rnes of impiety. When the foole commeth to ſay in his bears,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 14.1.</note> there is no God, then hee corrupteth all his waies, and doth abominable.</p>
               <p>The common argument for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe is, to crie out vpon others, as the cauſe of their wickedneſſe. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> laid the fault vpon his wife; <hi>Eua</hi> vpon the Serpent; the Serpent vpon God: and to this day, one man layeth the fault vpon another; like y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> theeues at the gallowes, that there exclaim againſt their parents,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:3077:61"/>and euill companions. But if I may be thought worthie to giue aduiſe, lay the blame where blame is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie; euen vpon thy vncleane and corrupted heart. For not iniected ſinnes by Satan, and the wicked by temptation; but aſcondent ſinnes, ariſing from thy heart, and from thine owne euill luſts, hath ſchoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thee to wickedneſſe. Therfore crie not out of others without thee; woe worth ſuch an one, that brought me to this:<note place="margin">Pſalm. 55.11.</note> But with
<hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> crie out, Woe worth my wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and vncleane hart. Surely, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſuch an one did not cauſe
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to doe this euill; but it was thou, O my vncleane heart; euen my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, that I could not put away, whom I made my guide and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar. Thus make thy ſelfe to know thy miſerie: And the God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen waſh all our hearts from wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. Wherefore heale vs (O Lord) and we ſhall be whole; ſaue vs (O Lord) and we ſhall be ſaued: doe thou (O King of heauen) purge
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:3077:61"/>vs, and we ſhall be cleane: and doe thou (O heauenly Father) in the pretious blood of Chriſt Ieſus, waſh vs, and wee ſhall bee whiter then ſnow.</p>
               <p>And ſo I haſte,<note place="margin">5. <hi>Circ.</hi>
                  </note> (becauſe time haſtes away) vnto the laſt point in the firſt branch, laying forth the obiect, ſhewing, from what the hart muſt be cleanſed:
<hi>O Ieruſalem, waſh thy heart from wickedneſſe,</hi> (or from euill) as ſome tranſlations haue it.</p>
               <p>I will not ſtand here to define, or diſtinguiſh ſinne.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.4.</note> What the tongue of Canaan calleth, <hi>Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n,</hi> and
<hi>Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>h,</hi> or
<hi>Paſchaah,</hi> iniquitie and wickedneſſe; that the Grecians call
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſinne; and the holy Ghoſt ſaith; that
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of the law. Which way ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it bee vnderſtood, it conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the people of Ieruſalem, of their ſinnes againſt God. Pointing forth vnto vs this truth.</p>
               <p>That the beſt, and readieſt way,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dost.</hi> 1.</note> to bring people from their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanneſſe, vnto repentance is, firſt,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:3077:62"/>that the Miniſter do labour to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince them of their ſine, they haue committed, before either he exhort them to holy life, or comfort them with the glad tidings of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. This courſe is here take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by our Prophet; it is my text; it is my exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to follow.<note place="margin">Ezech. 16 2. &amp; 13 4.11.18. 1 Reg. 18.18. Matth. 3.7.</note> It was that which God incharged <hi>Exachael</hi> with, this courſe did
<hi>Elias</hi> take with <hi>Aliab;</hi> and which <hi>Iohn</hi> the
<hi>Baptiſt</hi> tooke with the rebellious Iewes. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny ſpeake and preach <hi>(placentia)</hi> mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and merrie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſome cry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, repent and amend &amp; other thunder forth like <hi>Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>arges,</hi> the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, as the ſons of thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; all which ought to bee done. But firſt (ſaith our Prophes) ſhew them what they haue done, and what is amiſſe, or all is in vaine, and done amiſſe, that is done.</p>
               <p>We liue in a captious age, where if people be generally reproued for ſinne;<note place="margin">Malac. 3.13.</note> they will anſwere, as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in <hi>Malachy</hi> did, <hi>What haue wee ſpoken againſt there?</hi> But if wee ſay
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:3077:62"/>you are ſinners, &amp; ſhew you wherin you haue ſinned; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhall cauſe you to bluſh with ſhame, and moue you with <hi>Dauid,</hi> to ſay, <hi>peecam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>Cain</hi> muſt be told of his
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;<note place="margin">Gen. 4. 1. Sam 15. &amp; 2.12.7. Ioh. 4. Act. 9.</note>
                  <hi>Saul</hi> of his diſobodience, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> of his adultery; the woman of Samaria, of her vncloane lift; and <hi>Paul</hi> muſt bee plainly told of his perſecution, or our heater will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer returne vuto vs,<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.19.</note> (Syr) I ſee that you are a Prophet. For then may the Preacher hope to profit by his publike doctrine, and the brother, by his priuate counſell; where firſt they ſhall proue to their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that of this and that ſinne, they are guiltle.</p>
               <p>For if the doctrine be only gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, men will miſ-apply it, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies turne it vpon others; ſoylog, he touched ſuch a man, and ſuch a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n to day, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>From this wiſedome I mind not to ſpeake of ſinne in generalls the originall corruption, and de f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of nature, which is an Fuhiop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:3077:63"/>skinne, that all the water of the ſes cannot waſh away. But I deſire to entreate particularly of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which is damnable to our ſelues, and hurtfull to others. And albeit here I might marſhall vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable troopes of tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I entreat your godly patience, that I may touch the ſores of our owne time. In which, (if you will but a little open your eyes) you ſhal ſee, <hi>Qui impià agent, ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> intelligent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> that will doe wickedly, and will not vnderſtand. And although I cannot touch all the flying ſinnes of Iudah, which make too loud a cryin the cares of God; yet ſome of them I purpoſe but to name: I beſeech you lend me your hearts to conſider of them, and teares of repentance, to waſh them away.</p>
               <p>Heere I meane not to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſall of the ſecret reuoltings from the truth of God; nor the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall embracing in corners, of the wilfull wil-worſhip, in ſtead of the ſeruice of God; nor the ſhamefull
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:3077:63"/>idolatrie, in trucking to Maſſe in the corners of the ſtreets, by ſeditious Papiſts, becauſe they are yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne: neither doe I minde to ſhew you, how impudently the knowledge of Gods mercy and truth is abuſed, wreſted, and tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled vnder feet, to the neglect of the poore, and ouerthrow of the helpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe: neither is it my purpoſe to remember you of the cruelty, and couetouſnes of the rich; nor of the irrefragable incorrigibility of the poore; nor of the incredulity, and contempt of Gods word amongſt all. Becauſe theſe be couertly carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the middeſt of vs, which, with the blood of <hi>Abel,</hi> crie to God, (as they appeare) for vengeance to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme; and which the late inunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of water, the ſtrange &amp; ſharpe winter, with the drie and ſcorching ſummer, cauſing the land to mourn, and the hearbs of euery field to wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">Ierem. 12.4</note> for the wickedneſſe of them that dwell therein, (not yet a yeere old) may moue vs to repentance.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:3077:64"/>But my purpoſe is, to bring into your preſence ſuch crying ſinnes, &amp; ſuch a diſorderly order of Roarers, within this your City, that partly the amendment, and partly the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation to you (my Lord) doth belong.</p>
               <p>It hath pleaſed God to make you Magiſtrates, and Fathers of this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; not only roſee that common e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie and quietnes be keps among the people; but alſo that God may haue his due honor and glory, both from you and them.</p>
               <p>Now among Superiours, for you to amend, the ſinnes and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes that the world taketh notice of, are eſpecially three. And in theſe the Prophet crieth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, whoſe ſcats be on high, to waſh your harts from wickedneſſe.</p>
               <p>And here by name, to ſhew you what ſinnes they be.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is Careleſneſſe, Lenitie, and neglect of Iuſtice.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond is, Couetouſneſſe, and Briberie.</p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:3077:64"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third is, Sacriledge, the Church-piercing ſinne.</p>
               <p>Againſt theſe the Prophet cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>O Ieruſalem, waſh thy heart,</hi> from theſe heauen-crying ſinnes: remoue theſe beames out of your owne eyes, that you may ſee the clearer to correct and reforme others.</p>
               <p>And here pardon me, if I be bold with my betters. For it is the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters dutie to diſcouer ſinne, and to conuince the conſcience of this and that wickednes, before he can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit them that he are him. This is the counſell that <hi>Ieremy</hi> receiued from the Lord, and deliuereth vnto vs; O City, waſh thy heart from wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, that thou mayeſt be ſaued. I deſire not here to ſit in any mans conſcience, for I haue learned no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to iudge of any, till I ſee what ſhall become of my ſelfe. Yet as we may not reueale all ſinnes, and diſcouer our fathers nakedneſſe, leſt the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed reioyce: ſo we may not couer ſome ſinnes, leſt the vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:3077:65"/>encreaſe. But if I may bee bold to ſhew you, what the Lord ſaith concerning theſe ſinnes; then I beſeech you to harken, and it ſhall not bee long, nor tedious to heare. The euill of the ſin of Careleſneſſe, too much Lenity, and neglect of Iuſtice; which bringeth in all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſinne, not masked, but with open face, into the Church, &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; and the ſame to bee committed with a high hand. For where haue you diſobedience to Magiſtrates, to Parents, to Maſters; where haue you drunkenneſſe, &amp;c. but where the Magiſtrate is care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of his office, or too milde in his office? When read you, or heard you, of the vnheard off ſinne, of deflouring of Virgins, of killing of old men, of braining of children, and of forcing of women, euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death; but when, &amp; where there is no magiſtrate;<note place="margin">Iudg. 4.1 &amp; 17.6. &amp;. 21.25.</note> as the holy Ghoſt ſaith, Iudg. 2.19.
<hi>there was then no King in Iſrael.</hi> When heare you ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, to bee puniſhed for the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:3077:65"/>ſinnes of inferiours; but when Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours waxe careleſſe of the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of iuſtice? For when magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates wax careleſſe of thoſe, that are committed to their charge, and neglect iuſtice to puniſh offenders; it is all one, as if there were no law, and no King in Iſrael. For then men become beaſts, and like <hi>Daniels</hi> flying Eagles with the wings of wickedneſſe, breaking into houſes,<note place="margin">Dan 7.</note> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> taking away lands, oppreſſing with vſurie, extortion, crueltie, deceit, blood and blaſphemie: theſe and much more, where iuſtice is not, roare in the ſtreetes; there is no care of God, nor feare of man, no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of law, nor order, nor regard of father, or mother, nor of Church, or Common-wealth, whether they ſtand or fall, ſo they may liue as they luſt. Hence it is, that ſo many or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants, widowes, and helpleſſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, crie out of the law, where the law is good and vpright: and all were well, if due execution were made of iuſtice.</p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:3077:66"/>
               <p>Therefore giue me leaue here to become the poore mans aduocate; nay the rich mans aduocate: yea all mens aduocates, but theirs, who are indeed beaſts; yea for the feare of God I entreat, that ye of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracie, who beare the ſword of iuſtice, would cut the wings of theſe lion-like beaſts: and ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the hornes of theſe yokeleſſe Belials, that they may bee ſet vpon their feete like men: and that from your graue and diſpenſing hand of iuſtice, mens hearts may be giuen them, that there bee no more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining, and that you may be free of their blood, ouer who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord hath ſet you. But doth this reſt with you only; or doe theſe euils ſhake the Common-wealth alone; and doth it not touch eccleſiaſticall offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and ſhake the Church alſo? Yea Prieſts and Ieſuites doe diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage the truth, increaſing daily, in writing and witneſſing to the diſgrace of true Chriſtianitie. For this alſo I humbly pray (in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:3077:66"/>behalfe) that you put y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good lawes in execution, againſt the fauourites of the Ieſuiticall brood: &amp; ſo doing, there wil be found as few Prieſts in England, as Snakes in Ireland.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Another ſinne, that ſome ſay at this day cleaueth to the ſonnes of God, they call Couetouſneſſe, a wickednes of receiuing gifts, blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the eyes of the wiſe. For mine owne part, as I cannot charge any, with the Prophet <hi>Iſay,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſai. 1.23.</note> that Rulers bee; becauſe I haue learned, not to haue as much as a diſre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thought of them; ſo I deſire you, that be ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ted amongſt the ſtarres, and be aboue others, to remember the fearfull iudgement, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſonnes of <hi>Ely</hi> brought vpon Iudah; and to thinke vpon the puniſhment that <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>biſes</hi> (<hi>Cyrus</hi> his ſonne) cauſed to be inflicted vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a bribing Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, whoſe skinne pulled ouer his cares, was hanged ouer the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate for an example.</p>
               <p>I beſeech you, let the feare of God, and the light of grace preuaile
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:3077:67"/>at leaſt (ſo farre) with all that be in authoritie, as the light of nature did with <hi>Lucius Valerius;</hi> who being Conſul of Rome, and dying whileſt hee was Conſul, hauing in his life time the cuſtodie of the treaſurie of Rome, was ſo free from inriching himſelfe, by vnlawfull meanes, that he was found ſo poore at his death, that the charge of his buriall was paied by the common people: ſo ſhall God, the world, and your own conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces teſtifie for you; that you haue waſhed your hearts from wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, and your fingers fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bribes.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. The third hurtful euil amo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g vs, is the ſinne of ſacriledge: which albeit, it be eſpecially in the richeſt perſons; yet it is a wickedneſſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt among al, and in each degree, one way or other. When I name ſacriledge, I name, a robber of God, a robber of Churches, a robber of the Common-wealth, a robber of bodies, a robber of ſoules: the name ſo ſhameful and horrid, that I bluſh to name, that which ſome in euerie
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:3077:67"/>ſex, ſtate and condition be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to commit. Fearfull it is to ſee and heare Patrons to deale with the Church-liuings, as <hi>Polymnestor</hi> did with <hi>Polydor;</hi> turne their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage into pillage, taking that which they neuer gaue, and reaping that which they neuer ſowed. For what the Palmer-worme hath left,<note place="margin">Ioel. 1.4</note> that hath the Graſhopper eaten; and the reſidue of the Graſhopper, hath the Canker-worme eaten; and the reſidue of the Canker-worme, hath the Catterpiller eaten. That which Impropriations haue left, that haue greedie Patrons eaten; and that which Patrons haue left, that haue euill cuſtomes deuoured; and that which cuſtomes haue left, that haue the couetous and wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling pariſhioners, as with the teeth of a lion, greedily gained. And vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe people grow kinder to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, they with their handfull of meale, and little oyle in the cruſe,<note place="margin">1. King. 17.12.</note> may mourning like, goe with the widow of Zareptha; and gather a
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:3077:68"/>few ſtickes, for (a few ſtickes will ſerue a little) to make a cake, and cate it, and dye. Oh that theſe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king hands might once ſee the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d againſt them, that wrote againſt
<hi>Balzazzar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 5
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 24</note> to take away from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as they haue taken from the Lord. The Iuſts of their vncleane hearts, haue defiled their hands, with the ſacriledge of <hi>Achan,</hi> to take gold and ſiluer and Babyloniſh garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,<note place="margin">Ioſua. 7
21.</note> of the ſpoyles of Iericho,<note place="margin">Pſal 74.7.8.</note> conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to God.</p>
               <p>But ſome may thinke it lawfull, for them to take their owne; which (they ſay) their parents in a blinde zeale gaue to the Church. It is fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to ſee children to ſit vpon their furthers, and to iudge the dead in the Lord.</p>
               <p>If any bee ſo paſt grace; let him know, that whatſoeuer is once law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully giuen to the maintenance of religion, may not bee taken away againe, vnder the paine of mortall ſinne. The text is euident: <hi>The field ſhall be holy to the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Leu. 27.21.</note> 
                  <hi>as a field ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:3077:68"/>from common vſes: the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion thereof ſhall be the Prieſts.</hi> And the Lord by <hi>Iool</hi> complaineth: <hi>Ye haue taken my ſiluer and gold, and haue carried into your temples my goodly &amp; pleaſant things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioel.
3.5.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is ſacriledge to tranſferre lands, houſes, priuiledges, or mony, violently, or couetouſly, or craftily to any other vſes, that hath been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the Church. And worſe, if worſe may be, is the maintaining of feathers, borders, chaines of gold, ſilke and veluet, with that, which did maintaine many poore; and with almes did feed and clothe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a fatherleſſe. Yet ſay ſome, what needs all this a doe for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Miniſterie; cannot Miniſters liue as the Apoſtles liued? To whom I anſwere, we can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if you will lay down, not your goods, but our owne goods at our feete, as the people did at the Apoſtles feete. O (deare brethren) will you haue vs ſhine like lampe, and take away our oyle? will you crie for preaching,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:3077:69"/>as children doe for bread; and will you muzzle the mouth of the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher? You will ſay to vs, that the world was neuer better, then when <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, <hi>Siluer and gold haue I none:</hi> and wil you not giue vs leaue to ſay, with the Ancient, that it is not indecent, to deſire,<note place="margin">Aug. de cra. D. o proba.</note>
                  <hi>ſufficientia vitae?</hi> Yea (with your leaue) we ſay more, that
<hi>Sublatis ſtudiorum pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mijs, etiam ſtudia pereunt:</hi> That lack of liuing, maketh lack of learning; and lacke of learning cauſeth Gods people to wander vpon the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, as ſheepe without able ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards. But yet me thinkes, I heare ſome to ſay, that Church-liuings be too large, and Church-mens hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes too great; for their reuenewes (ſay ſome clawbacke) will ſuffice a good Knight. I cannot fitter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare theſe then to
<hi>Dionyſius</hi> the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, who tooke the golden gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from
<hi>Iupiter Oly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pian</hi> in
<hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loponneſus,</hi> ſaying: That it was too heauie for ſommer, and too colde for winter: and therefore the God
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:3077:69"/>muſt be ſtripped, to clothe him: and leſt the God ſtand cleane naked, he ſhall bee clothed with a woolle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> rugge, light for ſommer, and warme for winter: for you muſt know that gold is too heauie for any, but for the beaſts of the earth to carry. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, in humilitie be it ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ſith <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Aaron</hi> by Gods ordinance went hand in hand, I ſee nothing from God to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, but we ought to haue an hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Miniſterie, as well as an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Magiſtracie: and that a good Miniſter be as well allowed, as a good Magiſtrate.</p>
               <p>Look to it, my beloued, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Miniſters and Preachers, hath alreadie wrought bad effects amongſt vs. Men, brethren and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, haue weeping eyes, and a king hearts, to ſee this in the floriſhing time of the Goſpell, leſt the Lord puniſh the land for the contempt of his ſeruants. For beleeue it, this ſinne maketh a way for Atheiſts, and Papiſts, and Vters, and New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:3077:70"/>for Solifidian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and Nullifidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: and to make this good, I might bring a cloud of Fathers, to prouoke you to cleanſe your harts from this wickedneſſe. But I feare, if theſe ſins be not reformed, God will enter into iudgment with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that haue taken the Lords houſes from him, into their poſſeſſions.</p>
               <p>And ſo much may ſuffice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Superiours, to be amended in themſelues.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sins in Iuſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours.</note> Now that God may haue his due honour (by your meanes) from the people, I ſhould name to you the wickedneſſe that rote in our ſtreets, and call to you (in the magiſtracy) for reformation, as to you the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe thereof (of right) belongs.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is the Prophan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion of the Sabbath.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond is, the taking of Gods name in vaine.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third is, Pride.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth is, Contention.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The fifth is, Contempt of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment.</p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:3077:70"/>
               <p>Theſe be the Roters, that grudge if they be not ſatisfied; they cauſe the land to mourne, and the graſſe of the earth to wither away; they will haſten the Lords vengeance, if ſpeedily they be not reformed.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For the firſt, touching the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, the Lord God hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and ſo doe the lawes of this Realme; yea ſo did the late com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable Proclamation of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouned Citie, that the Sabbath day ſhould be kept holy: that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould ceaſe from ſinne, as well as from labour; that they might ſerue God in trembling and feare, not thinking their owne thoughts, not ſpeaking their owne words vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lords holy day: But neglect of zealous executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of good lawes, ill cuſtome, and toleration hath brought it to paſſe, that the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude doe moſt ſhamefully prophane the Sabbath. Looke to it (I beſeech you) and ſuffer not your hearts to bee defiled with this wickednes. For not onely the Iewes and Turks
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:3077:71"/>crie ſhame of vs for this; but the very Papiſts make more of the Sat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terday, and Saints dayes, then wee doe of the Lords ſolemne feaſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond euill among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is, the taking of Gods name in vaine.</p>
               <p>Here I ſtand amazed, to conſider that the lawes of nations, haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken order for the vaine and idle ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the names of Princes in mens mouthes; ſo as none dare, but ſuch as are ſold to treaſon, ſpeake of their Kings, and States, but reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, &amp; with an vncouered head; and yet no law made againſt vaine ſwearing, and common blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the moſt ſacred name of the King of Kings. In mens ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary talke, lamentable it is to heare, in euery houſe, in euery ſhop, yea in euery ſtreet, how in ordinary talke euery one mingle words, and fill vp their ſentences with needleſſe oathes; as if that, which is of al ſins, a moſt notorious d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhonor to God, were but a ſmall ſinne, but much
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:3077:71"/>more horrible and odious is that blaſphemous and furious, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious ſwearing of many men; that if they be neuer ſo little offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and their mind diſpleaſed; then they fall to diſgorge their filthy ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, vpon the glorious name of their Creator. It is recorded by <hi>Herodot. lib.</hi> 6. that <hi>Nicanus</hi> pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a field on the Sabbath day a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Iewes; but for his blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie, loſt both the battell, and his life; and his head, his hands, and blaſphemous tongue was cut off, and hanged on the pinnacles of the Temple at Ieruſalem. And well worthie of greateſt ſhame, becauſe this vice of all other, carrieth with it the moſt deteſtation, for that it bringeth leaſt delight of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> other ſinnes. For all other vices a man may wring out ſome excuſe from nature, to leſſen the greatneſſe; but this admitteth no vaile at all. Is it not a deſperate caſe, for a man in mirth to ſweare by that blood, the remembrance of which, ſhould
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:3077:72"/>ſtrike ſorrow to the moſt obdurate hearts: that blood (I ſay) the loſſe of which gained redemption to the whole world. Me thinkes relen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoughts ſhould wound the heart of a Chriſtian, to name the wounds of Chriſt. But where reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is laid aſide, there deuotion is cold. But to heate your zeale, and to put an edge vpon your deuotion, remember what God ſaith, Mat. 23.23. I am bold to tell you in the Lords behalfe, that our tithing of Min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and Commin, and leauing the waightier parts of the Law vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looked vnto, is to bee feared, will draw the Lords wrath downe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs; and bring into our Cities, townes,<note place="margin">Zach. 5.4.</note> and houſes, <hi>Zacharies</hi> fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing booke, to conſume them with the timber and ſtones thereof. For it is decreed in heauen, that if thou wilt not keepe and do all the words of this Law (that are written in this booke) and feare this glorious and fearefull name,<note place="margin">Deut. 28.58.</note>
                  <hi>(the Lord thy God)</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord will make thy playne
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:3077:72"/>wonderfull, and the plagues of thy ſeed, euen great plagues, and of long continuance; and ſore diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and of long durance. For if it be true that <hi>Hoſea</hi> prophecieth;<note place="margin">Hoſea, 4.8.</note> then long ſince, becauſe of ſwearing, the Lord hath a controuerſie with the land. For who ſeeth not, that for oathes the land mourneth,<note place="margin">Ierem. 23.10.</note> and the inhabitants are ſmitten, and they feele it not?</p>
               <p>But the houre-glaſſe calleth mee to the pride of the Land.</p>
               <p>The prophet <hi>Zephaniah,</hi> 1.8. ſaith: <hi>It ſhall bee in the daye of the Lords wrath, that the Lord will viſit all ſuch, as are clothed with ſtrange apparell.</hi> Pride hath ſo many fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers added to her wings, that ſhee couereth all the earth with her ſhadow. If we looke to men, who ſhould be both wiſeſt, &amp; ſtrongeſt, they are growne ſo effeminate; and our women ſo manlike, that if it might bee, they would exchange kindes. What modeſt eye, can with patience behold the immodeſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:3077:73"/>and attires of our time: no ſooner is infancie put of, but impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie is put on. Many ſeemes to imitate
<hi>Nero</hi> in prodigality of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel,<note place="margin">Cap. 30</note> &amp; to verifie that in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, which was ſaid of him, by
<hi>Sueto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, In Nerone, nullam veſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us bis induſt.</hi> Many there be amongſt vs, that put not on one apparell, nor one faſhion twice, till at length they come to haue no apparell to put on. Many inuent faſhions to pleaſe the world; but the ſecret iudgement of God croſſeth their deſires; for they diſpleaſe, more then they pleaſe: but if their brauerie condemne them before men, in what caſe ſhall they ſtand before the Almighty?<note place="margin">Prou. 16.5.</note> The Wiſe man ſaith, All that are proud in heart, are an abomination to the Lord. The Lord reſiſteth the proud, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth grace to the humble. Worthy was the ſpeech of a Reuerend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of our time,<note place="margin">Doctor Babing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</note> that ſaid: If it be a ſhame to weare a paper on the hat at Weſtminſter hal, to declare what
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:3077:73"/>was done; it is as reprochfull to weare a vaine garment on the back, to pull all mens eyes vpon thee. O that the God of heauen) would moue you (in the Magiſtracy) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiue and put life into the many and good lawes concerning apparell; that men and women, in their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct callings, might bee knowne what manner of perſons they bee; that ſo honour (as ſhe is of her ſelfe bright and glorious) might haue her like raiment to her ſplendor; that ſo ſhe might be diſcerned from the baſe vulgars.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> I haue ſtayed you here too long, but I leaue the mother, and come to the daughter.</p>
               <p>The euill of Contention crieth for the rod of your correction. For this ſinne is the daughter of Pride. Onely through pride man cauſeth contention,<note place="margin">Prou. 13.10.</note> and by contention the land is diuided. O Lord heale the ſores thereof, for it ſhaketh. But co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tention is a coale, too hot for my cooling: I entreate you (in the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracie,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:3077:74"/>that your fountaines of diſcipline may flow forth, to waſh away this ſinne out of the Church and Common wealth. For it we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneth both Common-wealth, &amp; Church of God; yea it hindreth good proceedings; it troubleth the beſt ſubiects (that may be) that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and Atheiſts (in meane time) may doe what they liſt.</p>
               <p>The diuiſion betweene Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and Proteſtant; the alienati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of affection, betweene Miniſter, and Miniſter; that will neither vouchſafe to ſeeme to conſent, not ioyne together againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon aduerſarie, giueth aduant age to the Papiſts. But as the bleſſed Apoſtle ſaith to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.4.</note> ſo ſay I, There is but one body, one ſpirit, one hope of our calling, one Lord, one faith, one Baptiſme, one God, and one Father of all. If there be any conſolation in Chriſt, euen for his ſake that made vs, and for his blood that died for vs, let all theſe Ones, make vs one in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth;
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:3077:74"/>and while we liue, to keepe the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ſpirit, in the bond of peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The Laſt euill that waiteth for your check, &amp; needeth iron hands to puniſh the wickedneſſe thereof, is the contempt of you, that ſit in the high places. For the contempt of gouernment,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the contempt of God himſelfe. But the Papiſts will ſay, they may in ſome things diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey <hi>Caſar,</hi> and make no breach of their alleagiance to Almighty God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> But they that ſo ſay, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith) telleth a lie for the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The contrary I doe proteſt, that ſubiect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to Princes ſtandeth with, and is commanded in religion, by God himſelfe. For that which is <hi>Caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> ought to be giuen to <hi>Caſar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 22.21.</note> if wee will keep our allegiance to God; and the contempt of gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is a ſin by Saint <hi>Iud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> bound vp, in the bundle of death. Where you may reade, that none but filthy perſons, that need to be waſhed, cut and ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ned, doe deſpiſe gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whom Saint <hi>Peter</hi> calleth
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:3077:75"/>bruit beaſts, lead by ſenſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lltie, which haue no ground but igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: which if they pleade not, you ſhall doe well, to let them haue no mercie, but iuſtice.</p>
               <p>There be 2. poyſon ſome wormes that gaſter at the roote of gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and two beaſts amongſt vs, with Ants bellies, and <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>hes</hi> hands, like the horſeleach that will neuer be ſatisfied. And if you would know them by name; the one is, <hi>hath waſted all;</hi> the other, longeth to <hi>waſte all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hath waſted all,</hi> are the male-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented prodigals, that in euerie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree haue conſumed their owne eſtates: and now houer ouer other mens, and their eye watcheth for the twy-light: and of theſe ſome lie couchant and dormant.</p>
               <p>Concerning <hi>would waste all,</hi> or longeth to <hi>waste all,</hi> who haue trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured vp wrath and reuenge in their mindes, againſt Prince and people. Theſe (forſooth) crie out, that euery man muſt not be ſubiect to all, that
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:3077:75"/>bee in office, or ſuperioritie ouer him, by that he is a Superiour, and that onely in matters of peace and policie; but not in matters of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or regiment of ſoules.<note place="margin">Rhem. annot. in Rom. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> Theſe be the counterfeit Catholikes, that haue taken libertie, to change their ciuill Superiour, for a ſpirituall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and religion for policie, and policie for religion.</p>
               <p>The Lord Almighty look down vpon them, and in his wrath grant to as many among them as be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent, the day that <hi>Zachari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> prophecieth, vnto them, euen a day,<note place="margin">Zach. 14.12.</note> that their eyes ſhall ſinke in their holes, and their tongue confume in their mouth, and that their fleſh may conſume away, though they ſtand vpon their feete, becauſe they fight againſt Ieruſalem. In meane time (right Honourable) it lieth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, for the ſafetie of the Kings perſon, of the State, and your ſelues, to looke vnto them. For the cauſe of the contempt of the Magiſtrate, is the incorrigiblenes of the euill
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:3077:76"/>diſpoſed. Wherefore ſith lawes be the ſinewes of a Common-wealth;<note place="margin">Plato.</note> ſith they be a diuine gift; ſith they bee the bands of Cities;<note place="margin">Demoſt. Cicero. Plutar.</note> ſith they are the very life of the Common-wealth; and ſith the Magiſtrate is the life of the law: let me preuaile with you, in the Lords behalfe, to take the zeale of <hi>Phineas,</hi> and the courage of
<hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Ioſuh;</hi> and goe through your Citie, ſearch, and ſee, and you ſhall behold ſinne to be growne to a head; and therfore high time that you make head a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. You haue the ſword of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, you haue the law: who doth warrant the ſword of iuſtice, but the law? who defends the law, but the ſword of iuſtice? Let the ſword of iuſtice by the law be warranted, and ſpare it not, leſt your ſelues bee neglected: you are our Fathers, we are your children: ſpart your rod, and ſpill vs. The firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement that was giuen to man, after the creation, was the Law, and vpon breach of the Law, was the ſword
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:3077:76"/>giuen to reuenge iuſtice. If you that be in authoritie ſuffer it ruſt in the ſheath; you will be contemned, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice deſpiſed, the poore oppreſſed, and the whole Common-wealth confounded.</p>
               <p>I might here leade you to more abominations, then theſe: where, in drunkenneſſe, men become beaſts: and yet at this day, hee is not coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a man, that will not take away the image of man, and defile him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe therewith. Oh, the height of prophaneneſſe, that man ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer more ſacrifice to <hi>Bacchus,</hi> then to <hi>Iehouah!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I might ſhew you the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of whoring, euen in this citie; where many men proſtrate their bodies to vncleannes. Let me pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, if more ſoules of our youth periſh any other way, then this.</p>
               <p>From hence it is (right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) that the citie, the towne, and the countrie is filled with beggers, and ſturdie vngabonds, that haue more buſied the Magiſtracie to ſet
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:3077:77"/>foorth good orders, both for the relieuing of the one, and puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the other, then at this day are executed. For doe they not loyter in euery corner of your ſtreetes, as though there were neither lawes, nor officers to puniſh them: or as though there were more feare to diſpleaſe them, then God? But time biddeth me tell you, that by this time, there bee few that heare me, whoſe hearts bee not conuinced. And therefore I haſte to the vſe we are to make of this doctrine, which is three-fold.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> It bewraieth a popiſh ſlaunder, that chargeth the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land with preaching libertie to ſin: becauſe we preach iuſtification by faith in Chriſt only. By this that hath been ſpoken in the diſcouerie of ſin, euery one, that hath his eyes about him, and will ſee, may ſee that wee preach not faith alone, (namely, that is alone) though faith only. For wee affirme that no Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertine, Proteſtant, or diſſolute pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:3077:77"/>of the Goſpell, that liueth in any knowne ſinne; hath fellowſhip with Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> The ſecond vſe is, to teach thoſe that are entred into the bodie of Chriſts Church, and are called by that excellent and glorious name of Chriſtians, to put on ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to waſh their hearts from wickedneſſe; taking the counſell of the holy Ghoſt: <hi>If any be in Chriſt, let him be a new creature.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5 17. Pſal. 16 6</note> And let euery one that calleth vpon the name of the Lord, depart from ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie. Either leaue your ſinnes, or leaue calling of God Father. Leaue diſſimulation and hypocriſie; or leaue carrying of Bibles, running to preachings, and talking of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. Leaue off ſaying. Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which art in heauen, vnleſſe you will liue as his children in earth. For if yee call him Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which, without reſpect of perſons,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1 17</note> iudgeth according to euerie mans worke, paſſe the time of your dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling here in feare. I humbly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:3077:78"/>beſeech you, in the feare of God, looke into the vncleane cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of your hearts; and watch ouer your ſoules, that a falſe heart, and a wicked heart, be not ſhrouded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a ciuill behauiour. For the Lord will iudge vs,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 16.7.</note> according to that which is in our hearts.<note place="margin">Iere. 17.10.</note> The Lord beholdeth well enough, the rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of theſe golden apples of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and in due time will cauſe them to fall to their euerlaſting ſhame and confuſions. Let Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants, Church-papiſts, and politike Proteſtants, leaue off their Iudas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like countenances, habits and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, in their many Ceremonies and complements of hypocriſie, like <hi>Balam</hi> with his ſeuen Altars, and his ſeuen Rammes: for God ſeeth, for all that, much treacherie againſt King and Countrie, lurking in their hearts; becauſe moſt of the are better bred, and better read in <hi>Machianell,</hi> then in the Bible. They are outwardly men in print: yet for all that, to couetouſneſſe, ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:3077:78"/>prophana<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, ſwearing vainly, and ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring falſely; to pride, and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yea drunkenneſſe, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, to oppreſſe the true honeſt Proteſtants, to hoarding vp of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, corne, &amp; the neceſſarieſt things of the land; they are like
<hi>Aman</hi> ſicke for <hi>Thamar,</hi> though it coſt them their liues. Theſe be varniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Proteſtant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to ſanctitie, like <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> to Chriſt. They plot againſt the Common-wealth, and pariſhes where they dwell, as <hi>Ahab</hi> did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Naboth.</hi> Oh, my ſoule, keep thee from the way of theſe men: Search, trie and cleanſe thy waies, and purge thy heart from ſuch wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes. And this for the firſt part. I ſhould ſpeake of the Argument, which is the ſecond part, but the time is ſpent. Therfore let vs pray, that God would bleſſe, that which time hath taught.</p>
               <p>Thou God of heauen and earth, giue this that hath been ſpoken thy bleſſing, that it may be a ſauour of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:3077:79"/>life vnto life, to euery one of vs, if it be thy good will; and with the blood of our Lord Ieſus, cleanſe vs, and take vs out of this our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe; and bring vs to thy kingdome of holineſſe, where thine honour dwelleth: and that for Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt his ſake, to whom with thee, O bleſſed Father, and the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Spirit, be all honour, glorie, power, dominion, might, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, both now, and from hence-forth for euer. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:3077:79"/>
               <head>This ſecond part was not vttered, for lacke of time; yet thought fit by the Author to be annexed in the Print.</head>
               <p>NOw followeth the ſecond part of the Text, of Iudah: preſeruation in this life, and of his ſaluation in the life to come: in theſe words; <hi>That thou mayeſt bee ſaued, (or mayeſt be helped, or mayeſt be kept, &amp;c.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which in effect is as much, as if he ſhould haue ſaid: If you will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the voyce of the Lord, and waſh your hearts from wickedness then the Lord will defend you, and preſerue you aliue in this life, and will watch ouer you, with a reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging hand, to anoy and deſtroy all thoſe, that riſe againſt you in this world, and will giue you euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life and ſaluation, in the life to come.</p>
               <p>This being the meaning of the words; let vs not here dreame of
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:3077:80"/>ſaluation by workes. For all what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer we can doe, cannot deſerue any thing at Gods hands; becauſe all our workes are imperfect:<note place="margin">Iſa. 64.6</note> and it muſt be perfect obedience, that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riteth any thing in this life, much more that deſerueth the immeaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable waight of glory.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> But the doctrine for inſtruction, (if you pleaſe) may be this:</p>
               <p>That reformation of manners, and ſanctification of life, maketh vs fit and capable, though not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of the mercies of God: I ſay, although ſanctification maketh vs not worthie of the mercies of God, yet it maketh vs capable, both of ſauing grace, and of all the mercies and benefits of God whatſoeuer. For we are not fit to receiue mercy from God,<note place="margin">Iob 11.14.15.16.</note> till we haue repented.</p>
               <p>This is one with the Prophets counſell to <hi>Naaman: Waſh and bee cleane:</hi> So here, cleanſe your hearts from wickedneſſe and be ſaued. If our ſinnes doe ſeparate Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies from vs; then ſanctification
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:3077:80"/>and holineſſe, maketh vs fit and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the mercies of God, both for this, and a better life.<note place="margin">Iſa. 59.2 Ier. 5.25.</note> But the firſt is true; therefore the ſecond. If repentance keepeth vs from pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing and deſtruction; then holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe maketh vs at leaſt capable of Gods mercy; but the propoſition the holy Ghoſt giueth for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine:<note place="margin">Luk.
13.3.</note> 
                  <hi>For vnleſſe you repent, yee ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi> If without ſanctification, and regeneration, we cannot ſee the kingdome of God; then without ſanctification wee are not, nor cannot bee capable of the mercies of God. But the former Chriſt maketh good, Ioh. 3.3. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp;c. I beſeech you deepely conſider this, and remember it wel, that which no money, nor gold can doe, repentance and ſanctitie may do. As the ground is for ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, when it is ploughed; ſo a heart is for the Lord, when it is cleanſed.<note place="margin">Act. 11.28.</note> For ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity and holineſſe is the way to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, trouble much more to all other mercies of God whatſoeuer.</p>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:3077:81"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> The vſe of this doctrine is laid downe by the Prophet <hi>Ieremy,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:<note place="margin">Ierom.
25.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Turne againe now euery one from his euill way, and from the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of your inuentions; and you ſhall dwell in the land, that the Lord hath giuen vnto you, and to your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for euer and euer.</hi> That is, as we deſire to be the matter whereon Gods mercy ſhall worke; and as we deſire to liue euery one quietly vnder his owne vine; and if wee would continue in this land, which the Lord our God hath giuen vs; then we muſt euery one forſake his euill waies, amend our liues, and ſanctifie our ſelues, that we may be holy. Hath any of vs endured miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſuffered want; hath the plague threatened vs, famine pinched vs, theeues and robbers ſpoyled our goods; haue any of vs been rich, and now poore; haue we been vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſet with friends, and their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour turned into disfauour? conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der deeply the matter (O my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) and let vs at length learne
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:3077:81"/>the true way to remedie our euill, to procure our ſafety,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.12 13.</note> and encreaſe againe what wee haue loſt; let vs leaue off to doe euill, learne to doe well, that we may bee ſaued: let vs caſt off ſinne,<note place="margin">Hoſ.
5.15.</note> and all ſhall be amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and reſtored. Then ſhall the earth yeeld her encreaſe, and God, euen our God ſhall giue vs his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Another vſe hereof, in that, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification maketh vs capable of Gods mercies; that God will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer withdraw his mercy, from him that repenteth,<note place="margin">Zach.
1.3.</note> and amendeth his life. For the Lord hath promiſed it. <hi>Turne you vnto me.</hi> (ſaith the Lord of Hoaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>and I will turne vnto you,</hi> (ſaith the Lord of Hoſts). Feare not the aſſiſtance of God in any trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or triall, or death, or affliction,<note place="margin">Pſal.
89.4.24.28.33.</note> if thou haſt repented; for then thou ſhalt hold out to the end. For albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it thou maieſt ſlip and fall againe;<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.28.</note> yet thou, canſt not finally periſh:<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.23.</note> for all thy ſinnes committed, after thy true and found repentance,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.6.</note> ſhall
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:3077:82"/>not bee thought vpon. Which is that,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.8.</note> which the bleſſed Apoſtle gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth for comfort: <hi>If any man ſin, we haue an aduocate with the Father, Ieſus Chriſt the righteous.</hi> For Ieſus is not to bee tied onely to ſuch ſins, as neuer were committed before, but is alſo to ſinnes often fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: So that frailty, and not looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be the cauſe thereof. And an Article of our faith it is, to beleeue the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes; ſhall we gloſſe vpon it thus, that is, of ſuch ſinnes as I neuer committed but once? Surely if we doe, it muſt bee ſaid, curſed bee the gloſſe that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupteth the Text. For that Article compriſeth all ſinne, before Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and after Baptiſme; before repentance, and after repentance; for euer throughout the courſe of our liues, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Laſtly, the vſe may ſerue to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme our iudgements, that ſinne and wickedneſſe, cauſeth the Lord to tranſlate a people here and there, and to ſpew the vngodly out of
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:3077:82"/>their lands, goods, and dwellings. For the ſeauen nations,<note place="margin">Leuit. 18. 24.</note> which the Lord caſt out before Iſrael, were caſt out, becauſe they had defiled themſelues with ſinne.<note place="margin">verſ. 25</note> 
                  <hi>The land</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>is defiled; therefore I will viſit the wickedneſſe therof vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, and the land ſhall vomit out h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r inhabitants.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſ.
28.</note> 
                  <hi>For ſhall not the land ſpew you out, if yee defile it, as it ſpewed out the people, that were before you?</hi> and it is a commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſaying:<note place="margin">Leuit. 20.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Ye ſhall keepe therfore all mine ordinances, and all my iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and doe them, that the land whether I bring you to dwell therein, ſpew you not out.</hi> But me thinkes I heare ſome obiect, and ſay; If ſuch an one for his ſinnes bee caſt out of his houſe, land &amp; liuing; how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it to paſſe, that hee to whom the Lord hath giuen it, is as wicked as he that was caſt forth: I anſwere, It may ſo come to paſſe in the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God, that the rod, which the Lord vſeth to correct one for ſinne, may afterward it ſelfe bee throwee<note place="margin">Iſa. 10.5.12.</note>
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:3077:83"/>into the fier. Wherefore (I beſeech you) in the feare of God, euen as you would be preſerued aliue, and after this life, ſaued for euer, lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way Atheiſme, Heatheniſme, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſme, and Browniſme, with all ſin and wickedneſſe; and continew in the profeſſion of the Goſpell, that you may dwell in the Lords fauor, and inherit the land of the liuing for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> Againe, in that he ſaith,
<hi>that thou mayeſt be helped.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It may ſerue to teach vs, that all our righteouſneſſe, and all that wee doe in the ſeruice of God, bringeth no aduantage nor profit vnto God; but the end why God requireth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of vs, is for our owne good and welfare, prooued heere; ſanctitie is required of vs, but for our owne good, that wee may bee ſaued. If a man ſhould be an earneſt ſutor to his neighbour, and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune his neighbour, not for any thing for himſelf, but for his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours owne good; would not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:3077:83"/>man condemne that man of great follie, if hee ſhould reiect his requeſts: yet the Lord of heauen and earth daily importuneth vs, and that for our owne euerlaſting gaine (which is godlineſſe) to bring vs to eternall bliſſe; and wee turne the backe, and giue him the left eare; like graceleſſe children, vpon who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their parents beſtow many meanes, and much money, in ſchooling; and otherwiſe, to haue them thriue in learning, and trading; but all in vaine. Know (dear Chriſtians) that your comming to Church, and giuing your preſence at a Sermon, is not to countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the Preacher, nor to the glory of God onely, but it is for thine owne gaine, not only the gaine of ſpirituall graces, but of temporall good things alſo. For as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">Iob 22.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Is it any thing to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty that thou art righteous? is it profitable to him, that thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thy waies vpright:</hi> therefore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint thy ſelfe (I pray thee) with him, and make peace,<note place="margin">verſ. 21.</note> thereby thou
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:3077:84"/>ſhalt haue proſperitie. <hi>For if thou returne to the Almighty,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſ. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>thou ſhalt bee built vp; thou ſhalt lay vp gold for dust,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſ. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>and the gold of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phir, as the fliuts of the riuers. Yea the Almighty ſhall bee thy defence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſ. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>and thou ſhalt haue plentie of ſiluer.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 5.29.</note> Who can denie, and reade this, but that all,<note place="margin">Iob 35.7.</note> that the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 16.2. &amp; 50.12 &amp; 116.12.</note> is for our welfare, vnleſſe we will denie God himſelfe?</p>
               <p>The reaſon of this truth is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God is Almighty, and able to glorifie himſelfe without vs.</p>
               <p>But heere a queſtion may ariſe,<note place="margin">Mat.
3.9.</note> which is this; If our ſeruice doe not profit God, why doth the Lord require it, it ſeemeth he hath ſome reſpect to himſelfe?</p>
               <p>No ſuch matter. But when hee requireth vs to abſtaine from euill, and doe good, hee onely conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, what is good for vs, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for our ſaluation. Let vs doe well then, and the ſame ſhal returne to our ſelues for good: if we doe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, it ſhall returne to our loſſe.
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:3077:84"/>And this is that, which God giueth for doctrine to <hi>Cain,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 4.7.</note> 
                  <hi>If thou do well, ſhalt thou not bee accepted? and if thou doeſt not well, ſinne lieth at the doore.</hi> For it cannot be ſaid, that we can diminiſh any thing of God, or that wee can rob him of any thing he hath. Therefore a man (by all the ſinnes that hee committeth) ſhall hurt none ſo much as himſelfe; and likewiſe the profit that commeth of righteouſneſſe, returneth to his owne perſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> The firſt vſe ſerueth, to ſet forth vnto vs the ineſtimable goodneſſe and loue of our God towards vs, who ſoliciteth vs daily, that wee might doe our ſelues good. For he commandeth vs diligently, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth vnto vs how we ſhould liue. And all this hee doth, that hee may procure our wealth here, and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in heauen.</p>
               <p>O conſider (deare brethren) if any of you ſhould ſo ſerue your neighbour, without reſpect of your owne profit, and bee ſo carefull of
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:3077:85"/>another mans benefit, that you ſhould goe and ſolicite him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: You muſt do this and that, &amp;c. and ſo ſhould continue euery day to ſtirre him forward, and to ſet him in order vnto the buſineſſe, whereof no profit ſhould redound vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: were not this a token of a rare and ſingular loue? And euen ſo doth our God deale with vs; hee calleth vs by his word, wooeth vs by his Prophets, draweth vs by his Spirit, that he may pardon vs by his mercie, and ſaue vs in his ſonne, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his promiſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Wherefore (deare Chriſtians) let vs not looke for the bleſſings of God in this life, or for ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after this life, becauſe by our life holy, we haue done the things which the Lord hath commanded; and thero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by haue brought profit, gaine, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or glorie to God; for ſo to preſume for Gods fauour, is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption without cauſe; for wee can doe God no good with all our holy life. Neither let vs preſume in
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:3077:85"/>reſpect of God, for hee neuer hath done vs any euil. Neither let vs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume in reſpect of our ſelues, for there is nothing in vs, to moue vs to preſume of Gods mercie: for in vs, that is, in our nature dwelleth no good: for we cannot think a good thought as of our ſelues. If we had done God any good; or done more good, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the law we are bound to doe; or if God had done vs any euil, then we might haue preſumed, by the law of right and reaſon, and by the law written, that, God being bound to reward, or recompence, wee ought not to bee ſent emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie away: But being with vs now, as it is, there is not any thing in fleſh and blood, that may cauſe vs to preſume. Therefore let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme our iudgements, that in the day of our account before God, we muſt flie from our owne merits and deſeruings, be our workes neuer ſo many, or ſo glorious: for we bring no gaine nor profit to God by our righteouſneſſe. From whence (me
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:3077:86"/>thinkes) I heare ſome obiect and ſay: If God doe not gaine by our righteouſneſſe; then wee cannot hurt him, nor diminiſh his Maieſtie and glorie by our ſinfulnes. And then it is no matter how wee liue: nor any reaſon or iuſtice, that God ſhould condemne and caſt away the worke of his own hands, for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch things, that neither do him good nor hurt.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The obiection ſtandeth on three parts. The firſt queſtion is, whether wee doe hurt God, or diminiſh his glorie by our ſinnes?</p>
               <p>I anſwere, that our ſinnes cannot diminiſh the glorie of God. For God knoweth how to bring light out of darkneſſe, and to turne our ſinnes to the glorie of his Maieſtie,<note place="margin">Exo. 9.16.</note> as he did the ſin of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 9.17</note> againſt the Iſraelites.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond queſtion, which ſaith, it is no matter how we liue, if God be neither profited nor glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by it.</p>
               <p>I ſay, wee doe much diſhonour
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:3077:86"/>the ſacred word of God, which as it is holy, ſo in euery page, line and leaſe calleth vpon vs (as for a matter of weight, and of importance) to be rich in good workes: which though our holineſſe profit not God, yet, neuertheleſſe, God declareth that hee accepteth our doings, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth account of them, as though they were of ſome value. For which cauſe God likeneth himſelfe to a husbandman that hath a vineyard, who cauſeth it to bee dreſſed;<note place="margin">Mat. 21
33. and 13.4.</note> and hath a field, and reapeth corne of it: In which ſimilitudes, God decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,<note place="margin">Mar. 12 1.</note> that hee doth account our workes,<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.1</note> as ſweete and pleaſant ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices in his ſight: And to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage vs to the workes of charitie, he ſaith, that when we doe good to the poore,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.40.</note> it is as if wee did it euen to him, it is as if wee did it euen to him, and he accepteth it as done vnto himſelfe. Thus you ſee, that our God, to encourage vs to doe well, will accept things whereby he taketh no profit. And therefore doth require it, as though hee were
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:3077:87"/>the better by it, and alſo promiſeth that wee ſhall not leeſe our labour thereby, neither that it ſhall bee a thing vnprofitable for vs. Therfore that wee leade a good and a godly life, is a matter of great neceſſitie.</p>
               <p>Concerning the third part of the obiection, ſaying, that it is againſt reaſon and iuſtice, that God ſhould condemne and caſt away the worke of his owne hands, for ſuch things that neither doe him good nor hurt.</p>
               <p>I anſwere, that reaſon requireth ſinne to bee puniſhed; and iuſtice commandeth that the euill be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, and the righteous rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And the word of God ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in infinite places, that Gods glorie cannot bee leſſened,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.9.</note> nor his royall ſeruice diminiſhed, by infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting condigne puniſhment in the condemnation of the vngodly. For God is able of ſtones to raiſe vp children to <hi>Abraham.</hi> Wherefore let vs in the feare of God euery one endeuour to bee religious, if it bee
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:3077:87"/>but to, make the Common-wealth peaceable, and the kingdome hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, 1. Sam. 12.14.15. For the cauſe why <hi>Ahabs</hi> gouernment was not ſo good as <hi>Dauids;</hi> nor <hi>Rehoboamt</hi> ſo peaceable as <hi>Salomons;</hi> ſurely it was, becauſe the one was eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the law of God, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was mingled with filthie Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie. The one was gouerned in wickedneſſe, and the other in the feare of God. For the Lord ſaith. <hi>For the tranſgreſſion of the land<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 28.2.</note> 
                  <hi>there are many Princes; but by a man of vnderſtanding and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, a realme likewiſe endureth long.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, it ſerueth, to reproue A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, carnall Goſpellers and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants at large, that thinke God is bound &amp; beholding vnto them, if they doe but come to Church, to grace the Miniſterie with their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. But know for a certaine, whatſoeuer he be, that walketh af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the luſts of his eyes, and the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of his owne heart, when
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:3077:88"/>others ſhall be preſerued, hee ſhall periſh; and when others ſhall bee ſaued, he ſhall be damned. For the Lord Ieſus ſhall ſhew himſelfe from heauen with his mightie An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, in flaming fire, rendring ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance vnto them,<note place="margin">2. Theſ.
1.8.</note> that doe not know God, and which obey not vnto the Goſpell of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. And this our example, our Prophet and our text, crieth loud in our eares, <hi>O Ieruſalem, waſh thy heart from wickedneſſe, that thou maieſt be ſaued.</hi> Euen ſo, come Lord Ieſus, come quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3077:88"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3077:89"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3077:89"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
